<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description>Efficiency (a virtue) is the child of laziness and greed (both vices), while
much of our economic activity is devoted to preventing boredom in the idle
time created by increases in efficiency. To be human is to be a strange
creature indeed :)
</description><atom:link href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 11:45:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Stop Supporting Python 2.6 (For Free)</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/04/stop-supporting-python26.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Note: I'm speaking with my "CPython core developer" hat on in this article,
rather than my "Red Hat employee" one, although it's the latter role that
gave me broad visibility into the Fedora/RHEL/CentOS Python ecosystem)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Gaynor recently raised some
&lt;a href="https://alexgaynor.net/2015/mar/30/red-hat-open-source-community/"&gt;significant concerns&lt;/a&gt;
in relation to his perception that Red Hat expects the upstream community
to support our long term support releases for as long as we do, only without
getting paid for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not true, so I'm going to say it explicitly: if you're currently
supporting Python 2.6 for free because folks using RHEL 6 or one of its
derivatives say they need it, and this is proving to be a hassle for you,
then stop. If they complain, then point them at this post, as providing an
easily linkable reference for that purpose is one of the main reasons I'm
writing it. If they still don't like it, then you may want to further suggest
that they come argue with me about it, and leave you alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affected users have more options than they may realise, and upstream
open source developers shouldn't feel obliged to donate their own time to
help end users cope with organisations that aren't yet able to upgrade their
internal infrastructure in a more timely fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Red Hat Supported Python Upgrade Paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href="https://developerblog.redhat.com/2013/09/12/rhscl1-ga/"&gt;September 2013&lt;/a&gt;,
Red Hat Enterprise Linux subscriptions have included access to an additional
component called
&lt;a href="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-US/Red_Hat_Software_Collections/1/html/1.2_Release_Notes/chap-RHSCL.html#sect-RHSCL-About"&gt;Red Hat Software Collections&lt;/a&gt;. You can think of Software Collections roughly
as "virtualenv for the system package manager", providing access to newer
language runtimes (including Python 2.7 and 3.3), database runtimes, and
web server runtimes, all without interfering with the versions of those
integrated with (and used by) the operating system layer itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model (and the fact they're included with the base Red Hat Enterprise
Linux subscription) means that Red Hat subscribers are able to install
and use these newer runtimes without needing to upgrade the entire operating
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href="https://developerblog.redhat.com/2014/06/10/red-hat-enterprise-linux-7-now-generally-available/"&gt;June 2014&lt;/a&gt;,
Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 has also been available, including an upgrade of
the system Python to Python 2.7. The latest release of that is
&lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-continues-platform-innovation-general-availability-first-minor-release-red-hat-enterprise-linux-7"&gt;Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7.1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Red Hat subscriptions all include free upgrades to new releases, the main
barrier to deployment of these newer Python releases is
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinrkosar/status/583786245261754368"&gt;institutional inertia&lt;/a&gt;.
While it's entirely admirable that many upstream developers are generous
enough to help their end users work around this inertia, in the long run
doing so is detrimental for everyone concerned, as long term sustaining
engineering for old releases is genuinely demotivating for upstream
developers (it's a good job, but a lousy way to spend your free time), and
for end users, working around institutional inertia this way reduces the
pressure to actually get the situation addressed properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond Red Hat Enterprise Linux, Red Hat's portfolio also includes
both the &lt;a href="https://www.openshift.com/"&gt;OpenShift&lt;/a&gt; Platform-as-a-Service
offering and the &lt;a href="http://www.feedhenry.com/"&gt;Feed Henry&lt;/a&gt; Mobile Application
Platform. For many organisations looking to adopt an iterative approach to
web service development, those are going to be a better fit than deploying
directly to Red Hat Enterprise Linux and building a custom web service
management system around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Third Party Supported Python Upgrade Paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current Red Hat supported upgrade paths require administrative access to
a system. While it's aimed primarily at scientific users, the comprehensive
&lt;a href="https://store.continuum.io/cshop/anaconda/"&gt;Anaconda Python distribution&lt;/a&gt;
from Continuum Analytics is a good way to obtain prebuilt versions of Python
for Red Hat Enterprise Linux that can be installed by individual users
without administrative access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Strata 2015, Continuum's Python distribution not only featured in a
combined announcement regarding on-premise deployment of &lt;a href="http://redhatstorage.redhat.com/2015/02/17/deploying-pyspark-on-red-hat-storage-glusterfs/"&gt;Anaconda Cluster
together with Red Hat Storage&lt;/a&gt;,
but also in Microsoft's announcement of Python support in the
&lt;a href="http://continuum.io/blog/azureml"&gt;Azure Machine Learning service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For users that don't need a full scientific Python distribution, Continuum
Analytics also offer &lt;a href="http://continuum.io/downloads"&gt;miniconda&lt;/a&gt; which just
provides a Python runtime and the conda package manager, providing end users
with a cross-platform way to obtain and manage multiple Python runtimes
without needing administrative access to their systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Supported Python Upgrade Paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of providing upgrade paths for folks without an active Red Hat
subscription has also been taken into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-and-centos-join-forces"&gt;January 2014&lt;/a&gt;
Red Hat became an official sponsor of the long established CentOS project,
with the aim of providing a stable base for community open source innovation
above the operating system layer (this aim contrasts with the aims of the
Fedora project, which is intended primarily to drive innovation within the
operating system layer itself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CentOS 7 was originally released in
&lt;a href="http://seven.centos.org/2014/07/release-announcement-for-centos-7x86_64/"&gt;July 2014&lt;/a&gt;,
and the latest release, CentOS 7(1503), was just published (as the name
suggests) in
&lt;a href="http://seven.centos.org/2015/03/centos-7-1503-is-released/"&gt;March 2015&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For CentOS and other RHEL derivatives, the upstream project for Red Hat
Software Collections is hosted at softwarecollections.org, making these
collections available to the whole Fedora/RHEL/CentOS ecosystem, rather than
only being available to Red Hat subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folks running Fedora Rawhide that are particularly keen to be on the cutting
edge of Python can even obtain prerelease Python 3.5 nightly builds as a
software collection from Miro Hrončok's
&lt;a href="https://copr.fedoraproject.org/coprs/churchyard/python3-nightly/"&gt;Fedora COPR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to maintaining Fedora itself, the Fedora community also maintains
the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL"&gt;Extra Packages for Enterprise Linux&lt;/a&gt;
(EPEL) repositories, providing ready access to non-conflicting packages
beyond those in the set included in the base Red Hat Enterprise Linx and
CentOS releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Providing Commercial Red Hat Enterprise Linux Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If projects are regularly receiving requests for support on Red Hat Enterprise
Linux and derived platforms, and the developers involved are actively looking
to build a sustainable business around their software, then a steady stream
of these requests may represent an opportunity worth exploring. After all,
Red Hat's subscribers all appreciate the value that deploying commercially
supported open source software can bring to an organisation, and are
necessarily familiar with the use of software subscriptions to support
sustaining engineering and the ongoing development of new features for the
open source software that they deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key things that many customers are looking for is pre-release
integration testing to provide some level of assurance that the software
they deploy will work in their environment, while another is a secure
development and distribution pipeline that ensures that the software they
install is coming from organisations that they trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Red Hat's essential tools for managing this distributed integration
testing and content assurance effort is its
&lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/partners"&gt;Partner Program&lt;/a&gt;. This program is
designed to not only assist Red Hat subscribers in finding supported
software that meets their needs, but also to provide Red Hat, partners, and
customers with confidence that the components of deployed solutions will
work well together in target deployment environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically for web service developers that would like to provide a
supported on-premise offering, last year's announcement of a &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-announces-certification-for-containerized-applications-extends-customer-confidence-and-trust-to-the-cloud"&gt;Container Certification Program&lt;/a&gt;
(with Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 and the OpenShift Platform-as-a-Service
offering as certified container hosts) extended Red Hat's certification
programs to cover the certification of Docker containers in addition to
other forms of Linux application deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more recently, the
&lt;a href="http://connect.redhat.com/zones/containers"&gt;Red Hat Container Development Kit&lt;/a&gt;
was introduced to help streamline that certification process for Red Hat
Independent Software Vendor Partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these are all things that folks should only explore if they're
specifically interested in building a commercial support business around
their software. If users are trying to get long term maintenance support
for a community project for free, then upstream developers should be sending
a single unified message in response: don't assume you'll be able to run
new versions of open source software on old platforms unless you're
specifically paying someone to ensure that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying this because I work for a platform vendor that gets paid (at
least in part) to do this, I'm saying it because most open source projects
are maintained by innovators that are upgrading their technology stacks
regularly, where versions of components are already old after 2 years and
truly ancient after 5. Expecting open source innovators to provide long term
maintenance for free is simply unreasonable - regularly upgrading their own
stacks means they don't need this long term platform support for themselves,
so the folks that are seeking it should be expected to pay for it to happen.
(Apparent exceptions like CentOS aren't exceptions at all: sustaining
engineering on CentOS is instead a beneficial community byproduct of the
&lt;a href="http://crunchtools.com/deep-dive-rebase-vs-backport/"&gt;paid sustaining engineering&lt;/a&gt;
that goes into Red Hat Enterprise Linux).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/04/stop-supporting-python26.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 09:30:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Abusing Contributors is not OK</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/abuse-is-not-ok.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As reported in
&lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2015/01/linus-torvalds-on-why-he-isnt-nice-i-dont-care-about-you/"&gt;Ars Technica&lt;/a&gt;,
the ongoing efforts to promote diversity in open source communities came
up once more during the plenary Q&amp;amp;A session with Linus Torvalds, Andrew Tridgell,
Bdale Garbee and Rusty Russell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was there for that session, and found that Linus's response appeared to
betray a fundamental misunderstanding of the motives of many of the folks
pushing for increased diversity in the open source community, as well as a
lack of awareness of the terrible situations that can arise when leaders in a
community regularly demonstrate abusive behaviour without suffering any
significant consequences (just ask folks like Kathy Sierra, Zoe Quinn, Anita
Sarkeesian and Brianna Wu that have been subjected to sustained campaigns of
harassment largely for being women that dared to have and express an opinion
on the internet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the coordinator of the Python Software Foundation's contribution to the
linux.conf.au 2015 financial assistance program, and as someone with a deep
personal interest in the overall success of the open source community, I feel
it is important for me to state explicitly that I consider Linus's level of
ignorance around appropriate standards of community conduct to be unacceptable
in an open source community leader in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linus's defence of his abusive behaviour is that he's "not nice", and
"doesn't care about you". He does care deeply about his project, though,
and claims to be motivated primarily by wanting that to continue to be
successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be completely honest, the momentum behind the Linux juggernaut is now
large enough that Linus could likely decide to chuck it all in and spend the
rest of his life on a beach sipping cocktails without worrying about open
source politics, and people would figure out a way to ensure that Linux
continued to thrive and grow without him. Many a successful start-up has made
that transition when the founders leave, and there's no good reason to believe
an open source community would be fundamentally different in that regard. The
transition to a new leadership structure might be a little messy, but the
community would almost certainly figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there's still a lot of scope for Linus to influence &lt;em&gt;how fast&lt;/em&gt; Linux
grows, and on that front his words and actions suggest that he considers
being careless in his speech, without regard for the collateral damage
his verbal broadsides may be doing to his cause, more important than
having the most positive impact he is capable of having on the future growth
of the Linux kernel development project and the open source community at
large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's not (necessarily) about being nice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may surprise some folks to learn that I don't consider myself a nice human
either. My temper is formidable (I just keep it under control most of the
time, a task online communication makes easier by providing the ability to
walk away from the computer for a while), and any feelings of compassion I
have for others are more a product of years of deliberate practice and
hanging around with compassionate people than they are any particularly
strong innate knack for empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty sure that genuinely nice people do exist, and I assume
that one of their key motives for creating open, welcoming, inclusive
communities is because it's fundamentally the right thing to do. The main
reason I exclude myself from my assumed category of "nice people" is that,
while I acknowledge that motivation intellectually, it's not really one that
I feel viscerally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, what I do care about, passionately, is &lt;em&gt;helping the best ideas win&lt;/em&gt;
(where I include "feasible" as part of my definition of "best"). Not the
"best ideas from people willing to tolerate extensive personal abuse".
The best ideas anyone is willing to share with me, period. And I won't hear
those ideas unless I help create environments where all participants are
willing to speak up, not just those that are prepared to accept a blistering
verbal barrage from a powerful authority figure as a possible consequence of
attempting to participate. Those are upsetting enough when they come from
random strangers on the internet, when they come from someone with enormous
influence not only over you and your future career, but also your entire
industry, they can be devastating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The second order consequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it, my not-nice reason for advocating for more welcoming and
inclusive open source communities: because, from an engineering standpoint, I
consider "has a high level of tolerance for receiving personal abuse from
community leaders" to be an extraordinarily stupid filter to apply to your
pool of potential contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exhibiting abusive behaviour as a leader has additional consequences though,
and they can be even more problematic: by regularly demonstrating abusive
behaviour yourself, you end up normalising harassment within your community
in general, both in public and in private.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe Linus when he says he doesn't care about who people are or where
they're from, only their contributions. I'm the same way - until I've known
them for a while, I tend to care about contributors and potential
contributors wholesale (i.e. happy people that enjoy the environment
they're participating in tend to spend more time engaged, learn faster,
produce superior contributions, and more quickly reach the point of being
able to contribute independently), rather than retail (i.e. I care about my
friends because they're my friends, regardless of context).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you're personally abusive as a leader, you also have to take a high
level of responsibility for all the folks that look up to you as a role
model, and act out the same behaviours you exhibit in public. When you reach
this point, the preconditions for participation in your community now include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willing to tolerate public personal abuse from project leaders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willing to tolerate public personal abuse from the community at large&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willing to tolerate personal abuse in private&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With clauses like that as part of the definition, the claim of "meritocracy"
starts to feel a little shaky, doesn't it? Meritocracy is a fine ideal
to strive for, but claiming to have achieved it when you're imposing
irrelevant requirements like this is arrogant nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not done yet, though, as this culture of abuse then combines with
elitism based on previously acquired knowledge to make it normal to &lt;em&gt;abuse
newcomers for still being in the process of learning&lt;/em&gt;. I find it hard to
conceive of a more effective approach to keeping people from adopting
something you're giving away for free than tolerating a community that
publicly abuses people for not magically already knowing how to use
technology that they may have never even heard of before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of this perspective, the only time I'll endeavour to eject anyone
from a community where I have significant influence is when they're actively
creating an unpleasant environment for other participants, and demonstrate no
remorse whatsoever regarding the negative impact their actions are having on
the overall collaborative effort. I count myself incredibly fortunate to
have only had to do this a few times in my life so far, but it's something
I believe in strongly enough for it to have been the basis for once deciding
to resign from a position paying a six-figure salary at a company I otherwise
loved working for. To that company's credit, the abusive leader was let go
not long afterwards, but the whole secretive corporate system is rigged such
that these toxic "leaders" can usually quickly find new positions elsewhere
and hence new subordinates to make miserable - the fact that I'm not willing
to name names here for fear of the professional consequences is just one more
example of how the system is largely set up to protect abusive leaders rather
than holding them to account for the impact their actions have on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ideas and code are still fair game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the spurious fears raised against the apparently radical notion of
refusing to tolerate personal abuse in a collaborative environment is that
adopting civil communication practices somehow means that bad &lt;em&gt;code&lt;/em&gt; must
then be accepted into the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminating personal abuse doesn't mean eliminating rigorous critique of
code and ideas. It just means making sure that you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; critiquing the
code and the ideas, rather than tearing down the person contributing them.
It's the difference between "This code isn't any good, here are the problems
with it, I'm confident you can do better on your next attempt" (last part
optional but usually beneficial when it comes to growing your contributor
community) and "This code is terrible, how dare you befoul my presence with
it, begone from my sight, worm!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter response may be a funny joke if done in private between close
friends, but when it's done in public, in front of a large number of
onlookers who don't know either the sender or the recipient personally, it
sets an astoundingly bad example as to what a mutually beneficial
collaborative peer relationship should look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you don't have the self-discipline needed to cope with the changing
context of our online interactions in the open source community? Well,
perhaps you don't yet have the temperament needed to be an open source leader
on an internet that is no longer the sole preserve of those of us that are
more interested in computers than we are in people. Most of the technical and
business press have yet to figure out that they can actually do a bit of
investigative journalism to see how well vendor rhetoric aligns with upstream
open source engineering activity (frequency of publication is still a far
more important performance metric for most journalists than questioning the
spin served up in corporate press releases), so the number of folks peering
into the open source development fishbowl is only going to grow over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn't &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; hard to learn the necessary self-control, though. It's mostly
just a matter of taking the time to read each email or code review comment,
look for the parts that are about the contributor rather than the code or the
design, and &lt;em&gt;remove them before hitting send&lt;/em&gt;. And if that means there's
nothing left? Then what you were about to send was pure noise, adding nothing
useful to the conversation, and hence best left unsent. Doing anything less
than this as a community leader is pure self-indulgence, putting your own
unwillingness to consider the consequences of your communications ahead of
the long term interests of your project. We're only talking about software
here, after all - lives aren't on the line when we're deciding how to respond
to a particular contribution, so we can afford to take a few moments to
review the messages we're about to send and consider how they're likely to
be perceived, both by the recipient, and by everyone else observing the
exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any personal abuse removed, you can be as ruthless about critiquing the
code and design as you like. Learning not to take critiques of your work
personally &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a necessary skill to acquire if your ambition is to become a
high profile open source developer - the compromises often necessary in the
real world of software design and development mean that you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; end up
shipping things that can legitimately be described as terrible, and you're
going to have to learn to be able to say "Yes, I know it's terrible, for
reasons X, Y, and Z, and I decided to publish it anyway. If you don't like
it, don't use it.". (I highly recommend giving talks about these areas you
know are terrible - they're fun to prepare, fun to give, and it's quite
entertaining seeing the horrified reactions when people realise I'm not
kidding when I say all software is terrible and computers don't actually
work, they just fake it fairly well through an ongoing series of horrible
hacks built atop other horrible hacks. I'm not surprised the Internet
breaks sometimes - given the decades of accumulated legacy hardware and
software we're building on and working around, it's thoroughly astonishing
that anything technology related ever works at all)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no matter how harsh your technical critiques get, never forget that
there's at least one other human on the far end of that code review or
email thread. Even if you don't personally care about &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;, do you really
think it's a good idea to go through life providing large numbers of people
with public evidence of why &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are a thoroughly unpleasant person to be
forced to deal with? As a project leader, do you really think you're going
to attract the best and brightest people, who are often free to spend their
time and energy however they like, if you set up a sign saying "You must be
willing to tolerate extensive personal abuse in order to participate here"?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What can we do about it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, and foremost, for those of us that &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; paid open source community
leaders, we can recognise that understanding and motivating our contributors
and potential contributors in order to grow our communities is &lt;em&gt;part of our
job&lt;/em&gt;. If we don't like that, if we'd prefer to be able to "just focus on the
code", to the degree where we're not willing to learn how to moderate our
own behaviour in accordance with our level of responsibility, then we need
to figure out how to reorganise things such that there's someone with better
people management and communication skills in a position to act as a buffer
between us and our respective communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we instead decide we need to better educate ourselves, then there are
plenty of resources available for us to do so. For folks just beginning to
explore questions of systemic bias and defaulting to exclusivity,
gender-based bias is a good one to start with, by perusing resources like the
&lt;a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Feminism_101"&gt;Feminism 101&lt;/a&gt; section on
the Geek Feminism wiki, or (if we have the opportunity) attending an
Ada Initiative
&lt;a href="http://adainitiative.org/what-we-do/workshops-and-training/"&gt;Ally Skills workshop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; acknowledge the importance of this work, then we can use our
influence to help it continue, whether that's by sponsoring educational
workshops, supporting financial assistance programs, ensuring suitable codes
of conduct are in place for our events and online communities, supporting
programs like the GNOME Outreach Program for Women, or organisations like
the Ada Initiative, and so on, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of us that &lt;em&gt;aren't&lt;/em&gt; community leaders, then one of the most
effective things we can do is vote with our feet: at last count, there are
over a million open source projects in existence, many of them are run in
such a way that participating in them is almost always a sheer pleasure,
and if no existing community grabs your interest, you always have the option
of starting your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal enjoyment is only one reason for participating in open source though,
and professional obligations or personal needs may bring us into contact with
project leaders and contributors that currently consider personal abuse to be
an acceptable way of interacting with their peers in a collaborative context.
If leaving isn't a viable option, then what can we do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the options I suggest above for community leaders are actually good
options for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; participants in the open source community that view the
overall growth and success of the free and open source software ethos as
being more important than any one individual's personal pride or reluctance to
educate themselves about issues that don't affect them personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we can hold our leaders to account. When community leaders give
presentations at community events, especially when presenting on community
management topics, feel free to ask the following questions (or variations
on these themes):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are we as community leaders aware of the impact current and historical
  structural inequalities have on the demographics of our community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What have we done recently as individuals to improve our understanding of
  these issues and their consequences?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What have we done recently as community leaders to attempt to counter the
  systemic biases adversely affecting the demographics of our communities?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are questions that open source community leaders &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be able to
answer. When we can't, I guess the silver lining is that it means we have
plenty of scope to get better at what we do. For members of vulnerable
groups, an inability for leaders to answer these questions is also a
strong sign as to which communities may not yet be able to provide safe
spaces for you to participate without experiencing harassment over your
identity rather than being critiqued solely based on the quality of your
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ask these questions, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get people complaining about bringing
politics into a technical environment. The folks complaining are simply wrong,
as the single most important factor driving the quality of our technology is
the quality of our thinking. Assuming we have attained meritocracy (aka "the
most effective collaborative environment possible") is sheer foolishness,
when a wide array of systemic biases remain in place that work to reduce the
depth, breadth, and hence quality, of our collective thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 22 Jan, 2015: Minor typo and grammar fixes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/abuse-is-not-ok.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 05:57:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>DTCA Public Consultation - Brisbane</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/dtca-public-consultation.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Asher Wolf
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Asher_Wolf/status/555909774596784129"&gt;alerted me&lt;/a&gt; (and
many others in the open source and cryptographic communities) to the
Australian Defence Trade Controls Act 2012, and the current public
consultation taking place around a bill proposing amendments to that act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being heavily involved in improving the security of open source
infrastructure like the &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/"&gt;Python Package Index&lt;/a&gt;
and the
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0466/"&gt;Python 2 reference interpreter&lt;/a&gt;,
working at a multinational open source vendor, and having an extensive
background in working under the constraints of the US International Traffic
in Arms regulations, Asher's concern caught my attention, since bad
legislation in this area can have significant chilling effects on legitimate
research and development activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I've escalated this legislation for review by the legal teams
at various open source companies and organisations, with a view to making
formal submissions to the
&lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/Consultation.asp"&gt;public consultation process&lt;/a&gt;
that is open until January 30th (ready for bills to be submitted for
consideration to federal parliament on February 23rd).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I was also able to attend the first public consultation session
held at the University of Queensland on January 19, so these are my
impressions based primarily on that sessions and my own experiences dealing
with ITAR. I'm not a lawyer and I haven't actually &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the legislation,
so I'm not going to pick up on any drafting errors, but I can at least speak
to the intent of the folks involved in moving this process forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to worry about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To folks encountering this kind of legislation for the first time, the
sheer scope of the
&lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/DSGL.asp"&gt;Defence and Strategic Goods List&lt;/a&gt;
can seem absolutely terrifying. This was very clear to me from some of the
questions various academics in the room were asking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this particular point, I can only say: &lt;em&gt;"Don't panic"&lt;/em&gt;. This isn't a
unique-to-Australia list, it's backed by a treaty called the
&lt;a href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt; - the DSGL represents
part of the implementation of that arrangement into Australian law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the laws implementing that arrangement are well drafted, everyone outside
the military industrial complex (and certain easily weaponised areas of
scientific research) can pretty much ignore them, while everyone
inside the military industrial complex (and the affected areas of research)
pays very close attention to them because we like not being in jail (and
because gunrunning is bad, and bioterrorism is worse, mmm'kay?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heavily regulated military supply chain is already scary enough, we &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
don't want to see the likely consequences of an unregulated one. (And if
you're tempted to make a snarky comment about the latter already being the
case, no, it really isn't. While folks can sometimes use overclassification
to avoid regulations they're supposed to be following, that still introduces
significant friction and inefficiencies into whatever they're doing. It's not
as good as people actually respecting the laws of the countries they're
supposedly defending, including genuinely meeting the requirement for
civilian authority over the military, but it's still a hell of a lot better
than nothing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting back on topic, the US ITAR and crypto export control laws are
currently considered the most strict implementation of the Wassenaar
Arrangement amongst the participating nations (going beyond the requirements
of the treaty in several areas), so if you see plenty of US nationals
participating in an activity without being fined and going to jail, you can
be fairly confident that it isn't actually a controlled activity under the
DSGL (or, even if it is, permits for that specific activity will be fairly
easy to get, and the most likely consequence of not realising you need a
permit for something you're doing will be someone from your government
getting in touch to point out that you should apply for one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certainly some very questionable aspects of this list (with the
perennial "favourite" being the fact the Wassenaar Arrangement does, in fact,
attempt to regulate the global trade in mathematics, which is just as stupid
and problematic as it sounds), but it's a known quantity, and one we're pretty
sure we can continue to live with (at least for the time being).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to worry about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real problem here is that the regulations included in the 2012 Act are
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; well drafted, and the legislated 2 year transition period from May 2013
through to May 2015 prior to the enforcement provisions kicking in is about
to run out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with the 2012 act is that in trying to keep things simple
(essentially, "if its on the DSGL, you need a permit"), it ended up becoming
extraordinarily draconian, requiring a permit for things that don't require
an export license even under ITAR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the general public, the most significant shift in the 2015 amendment bill
is the fact that several cases around open publication of information related
to dual-use technologies shift to being allowed by default, and only in
exceptional cases would a permit be required (and in those cases, the onus
would be on the government to inform the covered individuals of that
requirement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amendments also include a variety of additional exemptions for little
things like making it legal for Australian's own police and security agencies
to collaborate with their international counterparts. (Snarky comment
opportunity #2: in certain areas, making such collaboration illegal seems
like a potentially attractive idea...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That 2 year pilot was included in the original legislation as a safety
mechanism, the feedback from the associated steering group has been
extensive, and if things had gone according to plan, the relevant amendments
to the bill would have been passed last year in the spring sitting of federal
parliament, leaving DECO with at least 6 months to educate affected
organisations and individuals, and start issuing the now necessary permits
before the enforcement provisions became active in May. Unfortunately, we
currently have a federal government that views pushing a particular
ideological agenda as being more important than &lt;em&gt;actually doing their job&lt;/em&gt;,
so we're now faced with the prospect of regulations that industry doesn't
want, academia doesn't want, the Australian public service don't want, and
the Australian military don't want, coming into effect anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn't politics fun?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What DECO are (trying) to do about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group tasked with untangling this particular legislative Charlie Foxtrot
is the Australian Defence Export Control Office (DECO). Their proposal for
addressing the situation hinges on two bills that they plan to put before
the next sitting of federal parliament:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an amendment bill for the Act itself, which fixes it to be a conventional
  implementation of the Wassenaar Arrangement, in line with existing
  implementations in other Wassenaar nations (why we didn't just do that in
  the first place is beyond me, but at least DECO are trying to fix the
  mistake now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a second bill to delay the enactment of the enforcement provisions for
  a further six months to provide sufficient time for DECO to properly
  educate affected parties and start issuing permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I am aware, the second bill is needed primarily due to the
consideration of the first bill slipping by six months, since we're now
looking at the prospect of only having 4 weeks for DECO to start issuing
permits before the enforcement provisions come into effect. &lt;em&gt;Nobody&lt;/em&gt; involved
thinks that's a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If both of those bills pass promptly, then the only cause for concern is
whether or not there are any remaining devils in the details of the
legislation itself. Member of the general public aren't going to be able to
pick those up - despite the surface similarities, legalese isn't English, and
reading it without interpreting it in the context of relevant case law can be
a good way to get yourself into trouble. Summary translations from legalese
to English by a competent lawyer are a much safer bet, although still not
perfect. (For the programmers reading this: I personally find it useful
to think of legalese as source code that runs on the language interpreter of
a given nation's legal system, while the English translations are the code
comments and documentation that anyone should be able to read if they
understand the general concepts involved).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If at least the second bill passes, then we have another 6 months to work on
a better resolution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;neither&lt;/em&gt; bill passes, then DECO end up in a bad situation where they'll
be required by law to implement and enforce regulations that they're
convinced are a bad idea. They actually have everything in place to do that
if they have to, but they don't want this outcome, and neither does anyone
else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What industry and academia can do about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it's very short notice, the main thing industry and academia can do
is to file formal submissions with DECO as described in their overview of
the &lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/Consultation.asp"&gt;public consultation process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main things to be addressed on that front:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring federal parliament are aware of the importance of amending the
  Defence Trade Controls Act 2012 to eliminate the more draconian provisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring federal parliament are aware of the infeasibility of putting this
  into effect on the original timeline and the need for a significant delay
  in the introduction of the enforcement provisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring DECO are alerted to any remaining areas of concern in the
  specific drafting of the amended legislation (although I'd advise skipping
  this one if you're not a lawyer yourself - it's the functional equivalent
  of a lawyer with no training as a programmer proposing patches to the Linux
  kernel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were apparently asleep at the wheel when DTCA went through in 2012, so
we owe a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of thanks to whoever it was that advocated for and achieved
the inclusion of the two year transition and consultation period in the
original bill. Now we need to help ensure that our currently somewhat
dysfunctional federal parliament doesn't keep us from receiving the benefit
of that foresight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's definitely not going to happen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This consultation process is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the place to rail against the details of
the Wassenaar Arrangement or Australia's participation in it. You won't
achieve anything except to waste the time of folks that currently have a
really serious problem to fix, and a very limited window in which to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, Wassenaar has some serious problems, especially around its handling
of cryptography and cryptographic research, but we have a fairly settled
approach to handling that at this point in history. The critical concern in
this current case is to help DECO ensure that the associated Australian
regulations can be readily handled through the mechanisms that have already
been put in place to handle existing Wassenaar enforcement regimes in other
countries. With the way the 2012 Act was drafted, that's almost certainly
currently not the case, but the proposed 2015 amendments &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; fix it
(assuming the amendments actually have the effects that DECO has indicated
they're intended to).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/dtca-public-consultation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 12:41:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Running Kallithea on OpenShift</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/12/kallithea-on-openshift.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Kallithea for CPython&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CPython core development team are currently evaluating our options for
modernising our core development workflows to better match the standards
set by other projects and services like OpenStack and GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0474/"&gt;my own proposal&lt;/a&gt;
for that is to migrate a number of the support repositories currently hosted
using a basic Mercurial server on hg.python.org to an instance of
&lt;a href="https://kallithea-scm.org/"&gt;Kallithea&lt;/a&gt; hosted as forge.python.org.
(Kallithea is a GPLv3 Python project that was forked from RhodeCode after
certain aspects of the latter's commercialisation efforts started alienating
several members of their user and developer community)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tymoteusz Jankowski (a contributor to Allegro Group's open source data centre
inventory management system, &lt;a href="http://ralph.allegrogroup.com/"&gt;Ralph&lt;/a&gt;), has
already started looking at the steps that might be involved in integrating a
Kallithea instance into the PSF's Salt based
&lt;a href="https://github.com/xliiv/psf-salt/tree/kallithea"&gt;infrastructure automation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for my proposal to be as successful as I would like it to be, I need
the barriers to entry for the development and deployment of the upstream
Kallithea project itself to be as low as possible. One of the challenges
we've often had with gaining contributors to CPython infrastructure
maintenance is the relatively high barriers to entry for trying out service
changes and sharing them with others, so this time I plan to tackle that
concern &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt;, by ensuring that addressing it is a mandatory requirement
in my proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means tackling two particular problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a way to easily run local test instances for development and
  experimentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a way to easily share demonstration instances with others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first problem, I plan to rely on Vagrant and Docker, while for the
second I'll be relying on the free tier in Red Hat's OpenShift Online
service. Unfortunately, while the
&lt;a href="http://www.openshift.org/"&gt;next generation&lt;/a&gt; of OpenShift will support Docker
images natively, for the time being, I need to tackle these as two separate
problems, as there aren't any existing Docker based services I'm aware of
with a free tier that is similarly suited to the task of sharing development
prototypes for open source web services with a broad audience (let alone
any such services that are also
&lt;a href="https://github.com/openshift"&gt;fully open source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have these working to my satisfaction, I'll propose them to the
Kallithea team for inclusion in the Kallithea developer documentation, but
in the meantime I'll just document them here on the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enabling Kallithea deployment on OpenShift&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first priority is to get a public demonstration instance up and running
that I can start tweaking towards the CPython core development community's
needs (e.g. installing the custom repo hooks we run on hg.python.org), so
I'm starting by figuring out the OpenShift setup needed to run public
instances - the Vagrant/Docker based setup for local development will come
later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, WorldLine previously created an &lt;a href="https://github.com/worldline/openshift-rhodecode"&gt;OpenShift quickstart for
RhodeCode&lt;/a&gt; and published
it under the Apache License 2.0, so I was able to use that as a starting
point for my own
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ncoghlan/openshift-kallithea"&gt;Kallithea quickstart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I personally prefer to run Python web services under mod_wsgi in order
to take advantage of Apache's authentication &amp;amp; authorisation plugin ecosystem,
that's not a significant concern for the demonstration server use case I have
in mind here. There are also some other aspects in the WorldLine quickstart
I'd like to understand better and potentially change (like figuring out a
better way of installing git that doesn't involve hardcoding a particular
version), but again, not a big deal for demonstration instances - rather
than worrying about them too much, I just annotated them as &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; comments
in the OpenShift hook source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd also prefer to be running under the official Python 2.7 cartridge rather
than a DIY cartridge, but again, my focus at this point is on getting
something up and running, and then iterating from there to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That meant adapting the quickstart from RhodeCode to Kallithea was mostly
just a matter of changing the names of the various components being installed
and invoked, together with changing the actual installation and upgrade steps
to be based on Kallithea's deployment instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keys to this are the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ncoghlan/openshift-kallithea/blob/master/.openshift/action_hooks/build"&gt;build hook&lt;/a&gt;
and the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ncoghlan/openshift-kallithea/blob/master/.openshift/action_hooks/start"&gt;start hook&lt;/a&gt;.
The &lt;a href="https://developers.openshift.com/en/managing-action-hooks.html"&gt;OpenShift docs&lt;/a&gt;
have more details on the various available action hooks and when they're run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; comments noted above, I also added various comments
explaining &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; different parts of the action hook scripts were doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note: I haven't actually &lt;em&gt;tested&lt;/em&gt; an upgrade, only the initial
deployment described below, so I can't be sure I have actually adapted the
upgrade handling correctly yet)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deploying my own Kallithea instance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have an OpenShift account, so I could
&lt;a href="https://www.openshift.com/app/account/new"&gt;skip that step&lt;/a&gt;, and just
create a new app under my existing account. However, I didn't have the command
line tools installed, so that was the first step in creating my own instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;sudo yum install /usr/bin/rhc
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;yum is able to figure out on my behalf that it is &lt;code&gt;rubygems-rhc&lt;/code&gt; that
provides the command line tools for OpenShift in Fedora (alternatively,
I could have looked that up myself in the
&lt;a href="https://developers.openshift.com/en/getting-started-client-tools.html#fedora"&gt;OpenShift client tools installation docs&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to configure the command line tools to use my OpenShift
Online account, generate a local login token for this machine, and upload
my public SSH key to OpenShift Online. That process involved working through
the interactive prompts in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;rhc setup
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With those preliminary OpenShift steps out of the way, it was time to
move on to deploying the application itself. It's worth noting that
app creation automatically clones a local git repo named after the application,
so I created a separate "app_repos" subdirectory in my development directory
specifically so I could call my OpenShift app "kallithea" without conflicting
with my local clone of the main kallithea repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As described in the quickstart README, the app creation command is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;rhc app create kallithea diy-0.1 postgresql-9.2
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That churned away for a while, and then attempted to clone the app repo
locally over ssh (with SSH putting up a prompt to accept the validity of the
app's freshly generated SSH key). I'm not sure why, but for some reason that
automatic clone operation didn't work for me. &lt;code&gt;rhc&lt;/code&gt; put up a detailed
message explaining that the app creation had worked, but the clone step had
failed. Fortunately, as the troubleshooting notice suggested, a subsequent
&lt;code&gt;rhc git-clone kallithea&lt;/code&gt; worked as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenShift provides a default app skeleton automatically, but I actually
want to get rid of that and replace it with the contents of the quickstart
repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;rm -R diy .openshift misc README.md
git add .
git commit -m "Remove template files"
git remote add quickstart -m master https://github.com/ncoghlan/openshift-kallithea.git
git pull -s recursive -X theirs quickstart master
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The default merge commit message that popped up was fine, so I just accepted
that and moved on to the most interesting step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;git push
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because this is the first build, there's a lot of output related to
installing and building the PostgreSQL driver and git, before moving on
to installing Kallithea and its dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that still didn't take long, and completed without errors, so I now
have my own Kallithea instance
&lt;a href="http://kallithea-ncoghlan.rhcloud.com/"&gt;up and running&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And no, the default admin credentials created by the quickstart won't work
anymore - I immediately logged in to the admin account to change them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where to from here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various aspects of the current quickstart that are far from ideal,
but I don't plan to spend a lot of time worrying about it when I know that
support for using Docker images directly in OpenShift is coming at some
point in the not too distant future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key advantages of Docker is the much nicer approach it offers to
layered application development where infrastructure experts can provide
base images for others to build on, and in the case of deploying Python
applications with mod_wsgi, that means listening to Graham Dumpleton (the
author of mod_wsgi, currently working for New Relic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that front, Graham has actually been
&lt;a href="http://blog.dscpl.com.au/2014/12/hosting-python-wsgi-applications-using.html"&gt;working on&lt;/a&gt;
creating a set of Debian based
&lt;a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/grahamdumpleton/mod-wsgi-docker/"&gt;mod_wsgi Docker images&lt;/a&gt;
that Python developers can use, rather than having to build their own from
scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I'd really prefer something based on CentOS 7 or Fedora Cloud,
but that's a relatively minor quibble, and Graham's images should still make
a great basis for putting together a Vagrant+Docker based local workflow
for folks working on Kallithea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, however, is a topic for a future post :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>docker</category><category>kallithea</category><category>openshift</category><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/12/kallithea-on-openshift.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 03:18:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Seven billion seconds per second</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, YouTube put together their
&lt;a href="http://www.onehourpersecond.com/"&gt;"One hour per second"&lt;/a&gt; site, visualising
the fact that for every second of time that elapses, an hour of video is
uploaded to YouTube. Their
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/yt/press/statistics.html"&gt;current statistics page&lt;/a&gt;
indicates that figure is now up to 100 hours per minute (about 1.7 hours per
second).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressive numbers to be sure. However, there's another set of numbers I
personally consider significantly more impressive: every second, more than
seven billion seconds are added to the tally of collective human existence
on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about that for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 7 billion seconds of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 117 million minutes of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 2 million hours of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 81 thousand days of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 11 thousand weeks of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 222 years of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience, every single second, of every
single day. And as the world population grows, it's only going to get faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience per second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 centuries per minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;801 centuries per hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 millenia per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;135 millenia per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 billion years per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth in our collective human experience over the course of a single
year would stretch halfway back to the dawn of time if it was experienced
by an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We currently squander most of that potential. We allow a lot of it to be
wasted scrabbling for the basic means of survival like food, clean water and
shelter. We lock knowledge up behind closed doors, forcing people to reinvent
solutions to already solved problems because they can't afford the entry fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ascribe value to people based solely on their success in the resource
acquisition game that is the market economy, without acknowledging the large
degree to which sheer random chance is frequently the determinant in who wins
and who loses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We inflict bile and hate on people who have the temerity to say "I'm here,
I'm human, and I have a right to be heard", while being different from us.
We often focus on those superficial differences, rather than our underlying
common humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fight turf wars based on where we were born, the colour of our skin, and
which supernatural beings or economic doctrines we allow to guide our
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to change this? Is it possible to build a world where we
consider people to have inherent value &lt;em&gt;just because they're fellow
humans&lt;/em&gt;, rather than because of specific things they have done, or specific
roles they take up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly don't know, but it seems worthwhile to try. I certainly find it
hard to conceive of a better possible way to spend my own meagre slice of
those seven billion seconds per second :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>science</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 07:35:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The transition to multilingual programming</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/multilingual-programming.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2014-August/135873.html"&gt;recent thread&lt;/a&gt;
on python-dev prompted
&lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2014-August/135977.html"&gt;me to summarise&lt;/a&gt;
the current state of the ongoing industry wide transition from bilingual to
multilingual programming as it relates to Python's cross-platform support. It
also relates to the reasons why Python 3 turned out to be
&lt;a href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/python-4000.html"&gt;more disruptive&lt;/a&gt;
than the core development team initially expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good starting point for anyone interested in exploring this topic further
is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode#Origin_and_development"&gt;"Origin and development"&lt;/a&gt;
section of the Wikipedia article on Unicode, but I'll hit the key points
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Monolingual computing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At their core, computers only understand single bits. Everything above that
is based on conventions that ascribe higher level meanings to particular
sequences of bits. One particular important set of conventions for
communicating between humans and computers are "text encodings": conventions
that map particular sequences of bits to text in the actual languages humans
read and write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the oldest encodings still in common use is
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII"&gt;ASCII&lt;/a&gt; (which stands for "American
Standard Code for Information Interchange"), developed during the 1960's (it
just had its 50th birthday in 2013). This encoding maps the letters of the
English alphabet (in both upper and lower case), the decimal digits,
various punctuation characters and some additional "control codes" to the
128 numbers that can be encoded as a 7-bit sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many computer systems today still only work correctly with English - when
you encounter such a system, it's a fairly good bet that either the system
itself, or something it depends on, is limited to working with ASCII text.
(If you're &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; unlucky, you might even get to work with modal 5-bit
encodings like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ITA2#ITA2"&gt;ITA-2&lt;/a&gt;, as I have.
The legacy of the telegraph lives on!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working with local languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first attempts at dealing with this limitation of ASCII simply assigned
meanings to the full range of 8-bit sequences. Known collectively as
"Extended ASCII", each of these systems allowed for an additional 128
characters, which was enough to handle many European and Cyrillic scripts.
Even 256 characters was nowhere near sufficient to deal with Indic
or East Asian languages, however, so this time also saw a proliferation of
ASCII incompatible encodings like ShiftJIS, ISO-2022 and Big5. This is why
Python ships with support for
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/codecs.html#standard-encodings"&gt;dozens of codecs&lt;/a&gt;
from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proliferation of encodings required a way to tell software which
encoding should be used to read the data. For protocols that were originally
designed for communication between computers, agreeing on a common text
encoding is usually handled as part of the protocol. In cases where no
encoding information is supplied (or to handle cases where there is a
mismatch between the claimed encoding and the actual encoding), then
applications may make use of "encoding detection" algorithms, like those
provided by the &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/chardet"&gt;chardet&lt;/a&gt; package
for Python. These algorithms aren't perfect, but can give good answers when
given a sufficient amount of data to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local operating system interfaces, however, are a different story. Not
only don't they inherently convey encoding information, but the nature of
the problem is such that trying to use encoding detection isn't practical.
Two key systems arose in an attempt to deal with this problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows code pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;POSIX locale encodings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With both of these systems, a program would pick a code page or locale, and
use the corresponding text encoding to decide how to interpret text for
display to the user or combination with other text. This may include
deciding how to display information about the contents of the computer
itself (like listing the files in a directory).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental premise of these two systems is that the computer only needs
to speak the language of its immediate users. So, while the computer is
theoretically &lt;em&gt;capable&lt;/em&gt; of communicating in any language, it can effectively
only communicate with humans in one language at a time. All of the data a
given application was working with would need to be in a &lt;em&gt;consistent&lt;/em&gt;
encoding, or the result would be uninterpretable nonsense, something the
Japanese (and eventually everyone else) came to call
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mojibake"&gt;mojibake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn't a coincidence that the name for this concept came from an Asian
country: the encoding problems encountered there make the issues encountered
with European and Cyrillic languages look trivial by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this "bilingual computing" approach (so called because the
computer could generally handle English in addition to the local language)
causes some serious problems once you consider communicating &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt;
computers. While some of those problems were specific to network protocols,
there are some more serious ones that arise when dealing with nominally
"local" interfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;networked computing meant one username might be used across multiple
  systems, including different operating systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network drives allow a single file server to be accessed from multiple
  clients, including different operating systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;portable media (like DVDs and USB keys) allow the same filesystem to be
  accessed from multiple devices at different points in time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data synchronisation services like Dropbox need to faithfully replicate
  a filesystem hierarchy not only across different desktop environments,
  but also to mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these protocols that were originally designed only for local
interoperability communicating encoding information is generally difficult,
and it doesn't necessarily match the claimed encoding of the platform you're
running on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unicode and the rise of multilingual computing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The path to addressing the fundamental limitations of bilingual computing
actually started more than 25 years ago, back in the late 1980's. An initial
draft proposal for a 16-bit "universal encoding" was released in 1988, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode_Consortium"&gt;Unicode Consortium&lt;/a&gt; was
formed in early 1991 and the first volume of the first version of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode"&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; was published later that
same year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft added new text handling and operating system APIs to Windows based
on the 16-bit C level &lt;code&gt;wchar_t&lt;/code&gt; type, and Sun also adopted Unicode as part
of the core design of Java's approach to handling text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there was a problem. The original Unicode design had decided that
"16 bits ought to be enough for anybody" by restricting their target to
only modern scripts, and only frequently used characters within those
scripts. However, when you look at the "rarely used" Kanji and Han characters
for Japanese and Chinese, you find that they include many characters that
&lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; regularly used for the names of people and places - they're just
largely restricted to proper nouns, and so won't show up in a normal
vocabulary search. So Unicode 2.0 was defined in 1996, expanding the system
out to a maximum of 21 bits per code point (using up to 32 bits per code
point for storage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, Windows (including the CLR) and Java now use the little-endian
variant of UTF-16 to allow their text APIs to handle arbitrary Unicode code
points. The original 16-bit code space is now referred to as the Basic
Multilingual Plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While all that was going on, the POSIX world ended up adopting a different
strategy for migrating to full Unicode support: attempting to standardise on
the ASCII compatible UTF-8 text encoding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice between using UTF-8 and UTF-16-LE as the preferred local text
encoding involves some
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8#Advantages_and_disadvantages"&gt;complicated trade-offs&lt;/a&gt;,
and that's reflected in the fact that they have ended up being at the heart
of two competing approaches to multilingual computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing UTF-8 aims to treat formatting text for communication with the user
as "just a display issue". It's a low impact design that will "just work" for
a lot of software, but it comes at a price:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because encoding consistency checks are mostly avoided, data in different
  encodings may be freely concatenated and passed on to other applications.
  Such data is typically not usable by the receiving application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for interfaces without encoding information available, it is often
  necessary to assume an appropriate encoding in order to display information
  to the user, or to transform it to a different encoding for communication
  with another system that may not share the local system's encoding
  assumptions. These assumptions may not be correct, but won't necessarily
  cause an error - the data may just be silently misinterpreted as something
  other than what was originally intended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because data is generally decoded far from where it was introduced, it
  can be difficult to discover the origin of encoding errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a variable width encoding, it is more difficult to develop efficient
  string manipulation algorithms for UTF-8. Algorithms originally designed
  for fixed width encodings will no longer work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a specific instance of the previous point, it isn't possible to split
  UTF-8 encoded text at arbitrary locations. Care needs to be taken to ensure
  splits only occur at code point boundaries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UTF-16-LE shares the last two problem, but to a lesser degree (simply due to
the fact most commonly used code points are in the 16-bit Basic Multilingual
Plane). However, because it &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; generally suitable for use in network
protocols and file formats (without significant additional encoding markers),
the explicit decoding and encoding required encourages designs with a clear
separation between binary data (including encoded text) and decoded text
data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Through the lens of Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python and Unicode were born on opposites side of the Atlantic ocean at
roughly the same time (1991). The growing adoption of Unicode within the
computing industry has had a profound impact on the evolution of the
language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 1.x was purely a product of the bilingual computing era - it had no
support for Unicode based text handling at all, and was hence largely
limited to 8-bit ASCII compatible encodings for text processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 2.x was still primarily a product of the bilingual era, but added
multilingual support as an optional addon, in the form of the &lt;code&gt;unicode&lt;/code&gt;
type and support for a wide variety of text encodings.
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0100/"&gt;PEP 100&lt;/a&gt; goes into the many
technical details that needed to be covered in order to incorporate that
feature. With Python 2, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make multilingual programming work, but
it requires an active decision on the part of the application developer,
or at least that they follow the guidelines of a framework that handles the
problem on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Python 3.x is designed to be a native denizen of the
multilingual computing world. Support for multiple languages extends as far
as the variable naming system, such that languages other than English become
almost as well supported as English already was in Python 2. While the
English inspired keywords and the English naming in the standard library and
on the Python Package Index mean that Python's "native" language and the
preferred language for global collaboration will always be English, the new
design allows a lot more flexibility when working with data in other
languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider processing a data table where the headings are names of Japanese
individuals, and we'd like to use &lt;code&gt;collections.namedtuple&lt;/code&gt; to process
each row. Python 2 simply can't handle this task:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;collections&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;People&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"People"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;u"陽斗 慶子 七海"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"/usr/lib64/python2.7/collections.py"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;310&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;field_names&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;field_names&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;UnicodeEncodeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;'ascii'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;codec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;'t encode characters in position 0-1: ordinal not in range(128)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Users need to either restrict themselves to dictionary style lookups rather
than attribute access, or else used romanised versions of their names
(Haruto, Keiko, Nanami for the example). However, the case of "Haruto" is an
interesting one, as there at least 3 &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; ways of writing that as
Kanji (陽斗, 陽翔, 大翔), but they are all romanised as the same string
(Haruto). If you try to use romaaji to handle a data set that contains
more than one variant of that name, you're going to get spurious collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 3 takes a very different perspective on this problem. It says it
should just work, and it makes sure it does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;collections&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;People&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"People"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;u"陽斗 慶子 七海"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;People&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;陽斗&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;慶子&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;七海&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This change greatly expands the kinds of "data driven" use cases Python can
support in areas where the ASCII based assumptions of Python 2 would cause
serious problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 3 still needs to deal with improperly encoded data however, so it
provides a mechanism for arbitrary binary data to be "smuggled" through
text strings in the Unicode Private Use Area. This feature was added by
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0383/"&gt;PEP 383&lt;/a&gt; and is managed through
the &lt;code&gt;surrogateescape&lt;/code&gt; error handler, which is used by default on most
operating system interfaces. This recreates the old Python 2 behaviour of
passing improperly encoded data through unchanged when dealing solely with
local operating system interfaces, but complaining when such improperly
encoded data is injected into another interface. The codec error handling
system provides several tools to deal with these files, and we're looking
at adding a few more relevant convenience functions for Python 3.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying Unicode changes in Python 3 also made
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0393/"&gt;PEP 393&lt;/a&gt; possible, which changed
the way the CPython interpreter stores text internally. In Python 2, even
pure ASCII strings would consume four bytes per code point on Linux systems.
Using the "narrow build" option (as the Python 2 Windows builds from
python.org do) reduced that the only two bytes per code point when operating
within the Basic Multilingual Plane, but at the cost of potentially producing
&lt;em&gt;wrong answers&lt;/em&gt; when asked to operate on code points outside the Basic
Multilingual Plane. By contrast, starting with Python 3.3, CPython now
stores text internally using the smallest fixed width data unit possible.
That is, &lt;code&gt;latin-1&lt;/code&gt; text uses 8 bits per code point, &lt;code&gt;UCS-2&lt;/code&gt; (Basic
Multilingual Plane) text uses 16-bits per code point, and only text
containing code points outside the Basic Multilingual Plane will expand to
needing the full 32 bits per code point. This can not only significantly
reduce the amount of memory needed for multilingual applications, but may
also increase their speed as well (as reducing memory usage also reduces
the time spent copying data around).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are we there yet?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a word, no. Not for Python 3.4, and not for the computing industry at
large. We're much closer than we ever have been before, though. Most
POSIX systems now default to UTF-8 as their default encoding, and many
systems offer a &lt;code&gt;C.UTF-8&lt;/code&gt; locale as an alternative to the traditional
ASCII based &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; locale. When dealing solely with properly encoded data and
metadata, and properly configured systems, Python 3 should "just work", even
when exchanging data between different platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Python 3, the remaining challenges fall into a few areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helping existing Python 2 users adopt the optional multilingual features
  that will prepare them for eventual migration to Python 3 (as well as
  reassuring those users that don't wish to migrate that Python 2 is still
  fully supported, and will remain so for at least the next several years,
  and potentially longer for customers of commercial redistributors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding back some features for working entirely in the binary domain that
  were removed in the original Python 3 transition due to an initial
  assessment that they were operations that only made sense on text data
  (&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0361/"&gt;PEP 361&lt;/a&gt; summary:
  &lt;code&gt;bytes.__mod__&lt;/code&gt; is coming back in Python 3.5 as a valid binary domain
  operation, &lt;code&gt;bytes.format&lt;/code&gt; stays gone as an operation that only makes sense
  when working with actual text data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better handling of improperly decoded data, including poor encoding
  recommendations from the operating system (for example, Python 3.5 will
  be more sceptical when the operating system tells it the preferred encoding
  is &lt;code&gt;ASCII&lt;/code&gt; and will enable the &lt;code&gt;surrogateescape&lt;/code&gt; error handler on
  &lt;code&gt;sys.stdout&lt;/code&gt; when it occurs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eliminating most remaining usage of the legacy code page and locale
  encoding systems in the CPython interpreter (this most notably affects the
  Windows console interface and argument decoding on POSIX. While these
  aren't easy problems to solve, it will still hopefully be possible to
  address them for Python 3.5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More broadly, each major platform has its own significant challenges to
address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for POSIX systems, there are still a lot of systems that don't use UTF-8
  as the preferred encoding and the assumption of ASCII as the preferred
  encoding in the default &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; locale is positively archaic. There is
  also still a lot of POSIX software that still believes in the "text is
  just encoded bytes" assumption, and will happily produce mojibake that
  makes no sense to other applications or systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Windows, keeping the old 8-bit APIs around was deemed necessary for
  backwards compatibility, but this also means that there is still a lot of
  Windows software that simply doesn't handle multilingual computing
  correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for both Windows and the JVM, a fair amount of nominally multilingual
  software actually only works correctly with data in the basic multilingual
  plane. This is a smaller problem than not supporting multilingual computing
  at all, but was quite a noticeable problem in Python 2's own Windows
  support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mac OS X is the platform most tightly controlled by any one entity (Apple),
and they're actually in the best position out of all of the current major
platforms when it comes to handling multilingual computing correctly. They've
been one of the major drivers of Unicode since the beginning (two of the
authors of the initial Unicode proposal were Apple engineers), and were able
to force the necessary configuration changes on all their systems, rather
than having to work with an extensive network of OEM partners (Windows,
commercial Linux vendors) or relatively loose collaborations of individuals
and organisations (community Linux distributions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern mobile platforms are generally in a better position than desktop
operating systems, mostly by virtue of being newer, and hence defined after
Unicode was better understood. However, the UTF-8 vs UTF-16-LE distinction
for text handling exists even there, thanks to the Java inspired Dalvik VM
in Android (plus the cloud-backed nature of modern smartphones means you're
even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; likely to be encounter files from multiple machines when working
on a mobile device).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/multilingual-programming.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 06:16:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Python 4.0 won't be like Python 3.0</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/python-4000.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Newcomers to python-ideas occasionally make reference to the idea of
"Python 4000" when proposing backwards incompatible changes that don't
offer a clear migration path from currently legal Python 3 code. After all,
we allowed that kind of change for Python 3.0, so why wouldn't we allow it
for Python 4.0?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've heard that question enough times now (including the more concerned
phrasing "You made a big backwards compatibility break once, how do I know
you won't do it again?"), that I figured I'd record my answer here, so I'd
be able to refer people back to it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What are the current expectations for Python 4.0?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current expectation is that Python 4.0 will merely be "the release that
comes after Python 3.9". That's it. No profound changes to the language,
no major backwards compatibility breaks - going from Python 3.9 to 4.0
should be as uneventful as going from Python 3.3 to 3.4 (or from 2.6 to 2.7).
I even expect the stable Application Binary Interface (as first defined in
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0384/"&gt;PEP 384&lt;/a&gt;) to be preserved across
the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the current rate of language feature releases (roughly every 18 months),
that means we would likely see Python 4.0 some time in 2023, rather than
seeing Python 3.10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So how will Python continue to evolve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, nothing has changed about the Python Enhancement Proposal
process - backwards compatible changes are still proposed all the time, with
new modules (like &lt;code&gt;asyncio&lt;/code&gt;) and language features (like &lt;code&gt;yield from&lt;/code&gt;) being
added to enhance the capabilities available to Python applications. As time
goes by, Python 3 will continue to pull further ahead of Python 2 in terms
of the capabilities it offers by default, even if Python 2 users have access
to equivalent capabilities through third party modules or backports from
Python 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competing interpreter implementations and extensions will also continue to
explore different ways of enhancing Python, including PyPy's exploration of
JIT-compiler generation and software transactional memory, and the
scientific and data analysis community's exploration of array oriented
programming that takes full advantage of the vectorisation capabilities
offered by modern CPUs and GPUs. Integration with other virtual machine
runtimes (like the JVM and CLR) is also expected to improve with time,
especially as the inroads Python is making in the education sector are likely
to make it ever more popular as an embedded scripting language in larger
applications running in those environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For backwards incompatible changes,
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0387/"&gt;PEP 387&lt;/a&gt; provides a reasonable
overview of the approach that was used for years in the Python 2 series, and
still applies today: if a feature is identified as being excessively
problematic, then it may be deprecated and eventually removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a number of other changes have been made to the development and
release process that make it less likely that such deprecations will be
needed within the Python 3 series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the greater emphasis on the Python Package Index, as indicated by the
  collaboration between the CPython core development team and the Python
  Packaging Authority, as well as the bundling of the &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; installer with
  Python 3.4+, reduces the pressure to add modules to the standard library
  before they're sufficiently stable to accommodate the relatively slow
  language update cycle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the "provisional API" concept (introduced in
  &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0411/"&gt;PEP 411&lt;/a&gt;) makes it possible to
  apply a "settling in" period to libraries and APIs that are judged likely
  to benefit from broader feedback before offering the standard backwards
  compatibility guarantees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a lot of accumulated legacy behaviour really was cleared out in the Python
  3 transition, and the requirements for new additions to Python and the
  standard library are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; stricter now than they were in the Python 1.x
  and Python 2.x days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the widespread development of "single source" Python 2/3 libraries and
  frameworks strongly encourages the use of "documented deprecation" in
  Python 3, even when features are replaced with newer, preferred,
  alternatives. In these cases, a deprecation notice is placed in the
  documentation, suggesting the approach that is preferred for new code,
  but no programmatic deprecation warning is added. This allows existing
  code, including code supporting both Python 2 and Python 3, to be left
  unchanged (at the expense of new users potentially having slightly more
  to learn when tasked with maintaining existing code bases).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From (mostly) English to all written languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also worth noting that Python 3 wasn't expected to be as disruptive as
it turned out to be. Of all the backwards incompatible changes in Python 3,
many of the serious barriers to migration can be laid at the feet of one
little bullet point in
&lt;a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-3100/#atomic-types"&gt;PEP 3100&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make all strings be Unicode, and have a separate bytes() type. The new
  string type will be called 'str'.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PEP 3100 was the home for Python 3 changes that were considered sufficiently
non-controversial that no separate PEP was considered necessary. The reason
this particular change was considered non-controversial was because our
experience with Python 2 had shown that the authors of web and GUI frameworks
were right: dealing sensibly with Unicode as an &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; developer
means ensuring all text data is converted from binary as close to the system
boundary as possible, manipulated as text, and then converted back to binary
for output purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Python 2 doesn't encourage developers to write programs that
way - it blurs the boundaries between binary data and text extensively, and
makes it difficult for developers to keep the two separate in their heads,
let alone in their code. So web and GUI framework authors have to tell their
Python 2 users "always use Unicode text. If you don't, you may suffer from
obscure and hard to track down bugs when dealing with Unicode input".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 3 is different: it imposes a much greater separation between the
"binary domain" and the "text domain", making it easier to write normal
application code, while making it a bit harder to write code that works
with system boundaries where the distinction between binary and text data
can be substantially less clear. I've written in more detail
&lt;a href="http://python-notes.curiousefficiency.org/en/latest/python3/questions_and_answers.html#what-actually-changed-in-the-text-model-between-python-2-and-python-3"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;
regarding what actually changed in the text model between Python 2 and
Python 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This revolution in Python's Unicode support is taking place against a larger
background migration of computational text manipulation from the English-only
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII"&gt;ASCII&lt;/a&gt; (officially defined in 1963),
through the complexity of the "binary data + encoding declaration" model
(including the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Locale"&gt;C/POSIX locale&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_code_page"&gt;Windows code page&lt;/a&gt;
systems introduced in the late 1980's) and the initial 16-bit only
version of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode"&gt;Unicode standard&lt;/a&gt;
(released in 1991) to the relatively comprehensive modern Unicode code point
system (first defined in 1996, with new major updates released every few years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why mention this point? Because this switch to "Unicode by default" is the
most disruptive of the backwards incompatible changes in Python 3 and unlike
the others (which were more language specific), it is one small part of a
much larger industry wide change in how text data is represented and
manipulated. With the language specific issues cleared out by the Python 3
transition, a much higher barrier to entry for new language features compared
to the early days of Python and no other industry wide migrations on the
scale of switching from "binary data with an encoding" to Unicode for text
modelling currently in progress, I can't see any kind of change coming up
that would require a Python 3 style backwards compatibility break and
parallel support period. Instead, I expect we'll be able to accommodate any
future language evolution within the normal change management processes, and
any proposal that can't be handled that way will just get rejected as
imposing an unacceptably high cost on the community and the core development
team.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/python-4000.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 05:30:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Some Suggestions for Teaching Python</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/python-teaching-suggestions.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently had the chance to attend a Software Carpentry bootcamp at the
University of Queensland (as a teaching assistant), as well as seeing a
presentation from one of UQ's tutors at PyCon Australia 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many of the issues they encountered were inherent in the complexity
of teaching programming, a few seemed like things that could be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting floating point results from integer division&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python 2, integer division copies C in truncating the answer by default:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"print(3/4)"&lt;/span&gt;
    0
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Promoting to floating point requires type coercion, a command line flag
or a future import:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"print(float(3)/4)"&lt;/span&gt;
    0.75
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -Qnew -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"print(3/4)"&lt;/span&gt;
    0.75
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"from __future__ import division; print(3/4)"&lt;/span&gt;
    0.75
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Python 3 just does the right thing by default, so one way to avoid the
problem entirely is to teach Python 3 instead of Python 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python3 -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"print(3/4)"&lt;/span&gt;
    0.75
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(In both Python 2 and 3, the &lt;code&gt;//&lt;/code&gt; floor division operator explicitly
requests truncating division when it is desired)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Common Python 2/3 syntax for printing values&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been using Python 2 and 3 in parallel for more than 8 years now (while
Python 3.0 was released in 2008, the project started in earnest a couple
of years earlier than that, while Python 2.5 was still in development).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One essential trick I have learned in order to make regularly switching back
and forth feasible is to limit myself to the common print syntax that works
the same in both versions: passing a single argument surrounded by
parentheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -c &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'print("Hello world!")'&lt;/span&gt;
Hello world!
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python3 -c &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'print("Hello world!")'&lt;/span&gt;
Hello world!
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I need to pass multiple arguments, I'll use string formatting, rather
than the implicit concatenation feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python -c &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'print("{} {}{}".format("Hello", "world", "!"))'&lt;/span&gt;
Hello world!
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python3 -c &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'print("{} {}{}".format("Hello", "world", "!"))'&lt;/span&gt;
Hello world!
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rather than doing this, the Software Carpentry material that was used at the
bootcamp I attended used the legacy Python 2 only &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; syntax extensively,
causing examples that otherwise would have worked fine in either version to
fail for students that happened to be running Python 3. Adopting the shared
syntax for printing values could be enough to make the course largely
version independent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Distinguishing between returning and printing values&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem noted both at the bootcamp and by presenters at PyCon Australia
was the challenge of teaching students the difference between printing and
returning values. The problem is the "Print" part of the Read-Eval-Print-Loop
provided by Python's interactive interpreter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;print_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;return_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;print_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;return_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's no obvious difference in output at the interactive prompt, especially
for types like numbers where the results of &lt;code&gt;str&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;repr&lt;/code&gt; are the same.
Even when they're different, those differences may not be obvious to a
student:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;print_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Hello world"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Hello&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;return_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Hello world"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;'Hello world'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While I don't have a definitive answer for this one, an experiment that seems
worth trying to me is to teach students how to replace &lt;code&gt;sys.displayhook&lt;/code&gt;. In
particular, I suggest demonstrating the following change, and seeing if it
helps explain the difference between printing output for display to the user
and returning values for further processing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;new_displayhook&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"-&amp;gt; {!r}"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;displayhook&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;new_displayhook&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;print_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;return_arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Understanding the difference between printing and returning is essential to
learning to use functions effectively, and tweaking the display of results
this way may help make the difference more obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Addendum: IPython (including IPython Notebook)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial examples above focused on the standard CPython runtime, include
the default interactive interpreter. The IPython interactive interpreter,
including the IPython Notebook, has a couple of interesting differences in
behaviour that are relevant to the above comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; display return values and printed values differently,
prefacing &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; with an output reference number:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;In&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;In&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it has an optional "autocall" feature that allows a user to tell
IPython to automatically add the missing parentheses to a function call if
the user leaves them out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;ipython3 --autocall&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; -c &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"print 10"&lt;/span&gt;
-&amp;gt; print&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;10&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
10
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a general purpose feature that allows users to make their IPython
sessions behave more like languages that don't have first class functions
(most notably, IPython's autocall feature closely resembles MATLAB's
"command syntax" notation for calling functions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also has the side effect that users that use IPython, have autocall
enabled, and don't use any of the more esoteric quirks of the Python 2
&lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; statement (like stream redirection or suppressing the trailing
newline) may not even notice that &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; became an ordinary builtin in
Python 3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/08/python-teaching-suggestions.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 12:55:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Wielding Power</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making the usually implied disclaimer completely explicit on this one:
the views expressed in this article are my own, and do not necessarily
reflect the position of any organisations of which I am a member.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power is an interesting thing, and something that, as a society at large
(rather than the specialists that spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time thinking about it),
we really don't spend enough time giving serious consideration to. Trust and
fear, hope and despair, interwoven with the complex dynamics of
interpersonal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious kind of power is based on fear: people listening when you
tell them what to do, based on a fear of the consequences if they ignore
you. Many corporations have traditionally operated on this model: do what
you're told, or you'll be fired. "You might lose your job" then hangs as
an implicit threat behind every interaction with your management chain,
and a complex web of legal obligations and social safety nets has arisen
(to a greater or lesser degree in different countries) to help manage the
effectiveness of this threat and redress the power imbalance. Fear based
power is also, ultimately, the kind of power embodied in the legal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not the only kind of power though, and this post is largely about
another form of it: power based on &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Power based on trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear based power can be transferred fairly effectively: disobeying a
delegate can be punished as severely as disobeying the original authority
and so it goes. Interpersonal considerations don't get much consideration
in such environments - they're about getting the job done, without any real
concern for the feelings of the people doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency of that kind of centralised control degrades fairly quickly
though - with everyone being in constant fear of punishment, a whole lot
of effort ends up being expended on figuring out what the orders are,
communicating the orders, ensuring the orders have been followed, requesting
new orders when the situation changes, recording exactly what was done to
implement the orders and ensuring that if anything goes wrong it was the
original orders that were to blame rather than the people following them
and so on and so forth. It's like a human body that has no local reflexes,
but instead has to think through the idea of removing its hand from a
hotplate as an act of deliberate will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a different kind of power though, summed up well in this &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc"&gt;YouTube
video&lt;/a&gt;. What that kind of
power is based on is the idea that once people have their core survival
needs met, there are three key motivators that often work better than money:
autonomy, mastery and purpose. (Note: this is &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; core survival needs
are met. If people are still stressed about food, shelter, their health and
their personal relationships, then autonomy, mastery and purpose can go take
a hike)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its best, an environment based on autonomy, mastery and purpose is one
of mutual trust and respect. The purpose of the overall organisation and
its individual components is sufficiently well articulated that everyone
involved understands their responsibilities and how their efforts contribute
to the greater whole, individuals are given a high degree of autonomy in
determining how best to meet their obligations, and are supported in the
pursuit of the required mastery to fulfil those obligations as well as
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of distributed trust that Silicon Valley &lt;em&gt;tries&lt;/em&gt; to sum up
in its "move fast and break things" motto, but fails miserably in doing so.
The reason? Those last two words there: "break things". It's an
incredibly technocratic view of the world, and one that leaves out the
most important element of any situation: the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a key point many technologists miss: ultimately, &lt;em&gt;technology doesn't
matter&lt;/em&gt;. It is not an end unto itself - it is only ever a means to an end,
and that end will almost always be something related to people (we humans
are an egocentric bunch). When you "break things" you &lt;em&gt;hurt people&lt;/em&gt;, directly
or indirectly. Now, maybe those things needed to be broken (and a lot of
them do). Maybe those things were already hurting people, and the change
just shifts (and hopefully lessens) the burden. But the specific phrasing
in the Silicon Valley motto is one of cavalier irresponsibility, of freedom
from consequences. "Don't think about the people that may be hurt by your
actions - just move fast and break things, that's what we do here!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is NOT OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it needs to be OK to break things, whether deliberately or by mistake.
Without that, "autonomy" becomes a myth, and we are left with stagnation.
However, there's a difference between doing so carelessly, without
accounting for the impact on those that may be harmed by the chosen course
of action, and doing so while taking full responsibility for the harm your
actions may have caused .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, it's time to shift topics a bit. I assure you they're actually
related, which may become clearer further down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a corporation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The glib answer here would be "a toxic cesspool of humanity", and I'll grant
that's a fair description of a lot of them (see the earlier observations
regarding fear based power). I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; a capitalist though (albeit one that is
strongly in favour of redistributive tax systems), so I see more potential
for good in them than many other folks do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm going to give my perspective on the way some of the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt; ones
work when running smoothly, at least in regards to three roles: the Chief
Financial Officer, the Chief Technology Officer and the Chief Executive
Officer. (You may choose not to believe me when I say non-toxic corporations
are a real thing, but I assure you, such companies &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; exist, as most
people &lt;em&gt;don't actually like&lt;/em&gt; working for toxic cesspools of humanity. It's
just that fully avoiding the descent into toxicity as organisations grow is,
as yet, an unsolved problem in society. Radical transparency does seem to
help a lot, though. Something about the cleansing power of sunlight and
competing centres of power...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-toxic CFO role is pretty straightforward: their job is to make sure
that everyone gets paid, and the company not only survives, but thrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-toxic CTO role is also pretty straightforward: they're the ultimate
authority on the technological foundations of an organisation. What's on the
horizon that they need to be aware of? What's growing old and needs to be
phased out in favour of something more recent? What just needs a bit of
additional investment to bring it up to scratch?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of a CEO is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; less clear. "Finance" is pretty clear, as is
"Technology". But what does "Executive" mean? They're not just in charge
of the executives - they're in charge of the whole company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take on it? The CEO is ultimately the "keeper of the company culture".
They ultimately decide not only &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; gets done, but also &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it gets
done. While they have a lot of other important responsibilities, a key one in
my mind is that it is the CEO's job to make sure that both the CFO and CTO
remember to account for the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; that will ultimately be tasked with
handling "execution". They're the ones that say "no, we're not cutting
that, it's important to the way we operate - we need to find another way
to save money" (remember, we're only talking about the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt;
corporations here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when employees of a corporation expect that company to do the right
thing by them? They're trusting the CEO. Not the CFO. Not the CTO. The &lt;em&gt;CEO&lt;/em&gt;.
Arguably the key defining characteristic of a non-toxic corporation is that
the CEO is &lt;em&gt;worthy&lt;/em&gt; of that trust, as they will not only make those
commitments to their employees, but also put the mechanisms in place
to ensure the commitments are actually met. (This doesn't require any
kind-hearted altruism on the CEO's part, by the way. You can get the same
outcome through hard-nosed capitalism since making honest commitments to
your staff and then &lt;em&gt;keeping them&lt;/em&gt; is  what "our people are our greatest
asset" actually looks like in practice - it's just that a lot of
organisations that &lt;em&gt;say&lt;/em&gt; that don't actually &lt;em&gt;mean it&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commenting on other people's business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that brings us to the specific reason I sat down to write this article: a
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450396296289869825"&gt;tweet I posted&lt;/a&gt;
earlier today regarding Mozilla's public debate over the board's choice of
CEO. Specifically, I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would take Eich accepting the Mozilla CEO role to mean his personal
pride matters more to him than Mozilla's mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a pretty bold statement to make about someone I don't know and have
never even met, and in relation to an organisation that I don't have any
direct relationship with beyond being a user of their software and a fan
of their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the things I didn't suggest. I didn't suggest he resign from his
existing position as CTO. I didn't suggest that the Mozilla board withdraw
their offer of the CEO position. However, I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; state that, from my
perspective as an outsider that wants to see Mozilla execute on their
mission to the best of their ability, "trust me" is a sufficiently big call
to have to make for a role as critical as the CEO position that I don't
believe Eich should be asking that of his fellow members of the Mozilla
community. Actions have consequences, and one of those consequences can be
"No, you no longer have the right to request our trust - you actively hurt
us, and we don't believe you when you say you wish to make amends".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Eich's credit, he at least didn't just say "trust me", but rather made a
number of
&lt;a href="https://brendaneich.com/2014/03/inclusiveness-at-mozilla/"&gt;specific commitments&lt;/a&gt;.
However, the time to build that credibility in a relatively open organisation
is &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; accepting such a significant role, not after. Otherwise, there
will always be a lingering doubt for affected individuals that any public
statements are a matter of the responsibilities of the position, rather than
a genuine change in personal convictions. When it comes to matters like a
commitment to inclusiveness you &lt;em&gt;don't want&lt;/em&gt; a CEO that is going through
the motions out of a sense of obligation: this stuff is hard work and
tempting to skimp on, even when you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; care about it at a personal level
(as a case in point - it would have been &lt;em&gt;so much easier&lt;/em&gt; for me to not
comment on this situation at all, that I almost left it at just a couple
of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450381744227643392"&gt;vague&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450382065800728576"&gt;allusions&lt;/a&gt;
on Twitter rather than getting specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separating the personal from the professional is always difficult, and
few places moreso than the CEO role. During my tenure at Boeing, we had two
CEOs asked to resign due to unprofessional conduct. The military industrial
complex is a sordid mire of duplicitous misbehaviour and waste that makes
the open source technology community look like saints by comparison (and
I'll let you draw your own conclusions as to what it says about me
personally that I survived there for more than a decade), yet even they
were of the opinion that personal conduct &lt;em&gt;matters&lt;/em&gt; at the CEO level,
even moreso than in other less prominent roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, I personally do hope Eich's newfound commitment to
inclusiveness is genuine, and that the concerns raised regarding his
appointment as CEO prove to be unfounded. I'd prefer to live in a world
where the blog post linked above represents a genuine change of heart,
rather than being merely a tactical consideration to appease particular
groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, my opinion on this topic doesn't matter - it's now up to
Eich to demonstrate through his actions that he's worthy of the trust that
the Mozilla board have placed in him, and for concerned members of the
Mozilla community to decide whether they're willing to adopt a "wait and
see" approach as suggested, or if they consider that belated request in and
of itself to be an unacceptable breach of &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Change the Future - one small slice of PyCon US 2013</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2013/03/change-future-one-small-slice-of-pycon.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;"&gt;I'm currently kicking back in Red Hat's Mountain View office (I normally work from the Brisbane office in Australia) after a lovely lunch with some of the local Red Hatters, unwinding a bit and reflecting on an absolutely amazing week at PyCon US 2013 just down the road in Santa Clara.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For me, it started last Wednesday with the &lt;a href="http://python-notes.curiousefficiency.org/en/latest/conferences/pyconus2013/20130313-language-summit.html"&gt;Python Language Summit&lt;/a&gt; , an at-least-annual-sometimes-biannual get together of the developers of several major Python implementations, including CPython (the reference interpreter), PyPy, Jython and IronPython. Even with a full day, there were still a lot of interesting topics we didn't get to and will be thrashing out on the mailing lists as usual. However, good progress was made on a few of the more controversial items, and there are definitely exciting developments in store for Python 3.4 (due in early 2014, probably shortly after PyCon in Montreal if past history is anything to go by).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thursday was a real eye-opener for me. While I did have to duck out at one point for a meeting with a couple of the other CPython developers, I spent most of it helping out at the second of the &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/events/letslearnpython/"&gt;Young Coders&lt;/a&gt; tutorials run by &lt;a href="http://therealkatie.net/blog/2013/mar/19/pycon-2013-young-coders/"&gt;Katie Cunningham&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://mechanicalgirl.com/post/young-coders-learning-python-pycon-2013/"&gt;Barbara Shaurette&lt;/a&gt;. These tutorials were conducted using Raspberry Pi's with rented peripherals, and the kids attending received both the Pi they were using as well as a couple of introductory programming books.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Watching the class, and listening to Katie's and Barbara's feedback on what they need from us in the core substantially &lt;a href="http://mail.python.org/pipermail/python-dev/2013-March/124872.html"&gt;changed my perspective&lt;/a&gt; on what IDLE can (and, I think, should) become. Roger Serwy (the creator of IdleX, a version of IDLE with various improvements) has now been granted access to the CPython repo to streamline the process of fixing the reference implementation, and we're working on plans to make the behaviour of IDLE more consistent across all currently supported Python versions (including Python 2.7). (Some aspects of this, especially Roger's involvement, are similar to what happened years ago for Python 2.3 when Kurt B. Kaiser, the PSF's treasurer, shepherded the reintegration of the &lt;a href="http://idlefork.sourceforge.net/"&gt;IDLEfork&lt;/a&gt; project and its major enhancements to IDLE back into the reference IDLE implementation in the Python standard library). &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Friday saw the start of the conference proper, with inspirational keynotes from &lt;a href="http://www.pyvideo.org/video/1848/opening-statements"&gt;Jesse Noller &lt;/a&gt;(conference chair and PSF board member) on helping to change the future by changing the way we introduce the next generation to the computers that are now an ever-present aspect of our lives, and from &lt;a href="http://www.pyvideo.org/video/1668/keynote-2"&gt;Eben Upton&lt;/a&gt; (co-founder of the Raspberry Pi foundation), on how the Pi came to be the educational project it is today, and some thoughts on how it might evolve into the future.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Jesse's keynote included the announcement that every attendee (all 2500 of them) would be receiving a free Raspberry Pi, and that any Pi's that attendees didn't want to claim would be redistributed to various educational groups and programs. Not only that, but Jesse also announced &lt;a href="http://raspberry.io/"&gt;http://raspberry.io/&lt;/a&gt;, a new site for sharing Raspberry Pi based projects and resources, as well as a "Rasberry Pi Hack Lab" running for the duration of the conference, where attendees could hook their Pi's up to a keyboard and monitor, as well as experiment with various bits and pieces of electronics donated by one of the conference sponsors. &lt;a href="http://www.mechanicalcat.net/richard/log/Python/How_awesome_was_PyCon"&gt;Richard Jones&lt;/a&gt; also stepped up to run some additional short introductory PyGame tutorials in the lab (he had run a full 3 hour session on PyGame as part of the paid tutorials on the Wednesday and Thursday prior to the conference).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One key personal theme for the conference revolved around the fact that I've volunteered to be Guido's delegate in making the final decisions on how we reshape Python's packaging ecosystem in the lead up to the Python 3.4 release. I'll be writing quite a bit more on that topic over the coming weeks, so here I'll just note that it started with proposing some changes to the Python Enhancement Proposal process at the language summit on the Wednesday, continued through the announcement of the coming setuptools/distribute merger on Thursday, the "packaging and distribution" mini-summit I organised for developers on the Friday night, the "Directions in Packaging" &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/34/"&gt;Q&amp;amp;A panel&lt;/a&gt; we conducted on the Saturday afternoon, some wonderful discussions with Simeon Franklin &lt;a href="http://simeonfranklin.com/blog/2013/mar/17/my-pycon-2013-poster/"&gt;on his blog&lt;/a&gt; regarding the way the current packaging and distributions issues detract from Python's beginner friendliness and on into various interesting discussions, proposals and development at the sprints in the days following the conference.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Unfortunately, I didn't actually get to meet Simeon in person, even though I had flagged his poster as one I really wanted to go see during the poster session. Instead, I spent that time at the Red Hat booth in the PyCon Jobs Fair.  The Jobs Fair is a wonderful idea from the conference organisers that, along with the Expo Hall, recognises the multi-role nature of PyCon: as a community conference for sharing and learning (through the summits, scheduled talks, lightning talks, poster session, open spaces, paid tutorials, Young Coders sessions, Raspberry Pi hack lab, and sprints), as a way for sponsors to advertise their services to developers (through the Expo Hall and sponsor tutorials) and as a way for sponsors to recruit new developers (through the Jobs Fair). PyCon has long involved elements of all of these things (albeit perhaps not at the scale achieved this year), but having the separate Expo Hall and Jobs Fair helps keep sales and recruitment activity from bleeding into the community parts of the conference, while still giving sponsors a suitable opportunity to connect with the development community.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Both at the Jobs Fair and during the rest of the conference, I was explaining to anyone that was willing to listen what I see as Red Hat's role in bridging the vast gulf between open source software enthusiasts (professionals and amateurs alike) and people for whom software is merely a tool that either helps (hopefully) or hinders (unfortunately far too often) them in spending time on their actual job/project/hobby/etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I also spent a lot of time talking to people about my actual day job. I'm the development lead for &lt;a href="http://beaker-project.org/"&gt;one of the test systems&lt;/a&gt; at Red Hat, and while it is very good at what it does (full stack integration testing from hardware, through the OS and up into application software), it also needs to integrate well with other systems like autotest and OpenStack if we're going to avoid pointlessly reinventing a lot of very complicated wheels. Learning more about what those projects are currently capable of makes it easier for me to prioritize the things we work on, and make suitable choices about Beaker's overall architecture.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At the sprints, in addition to working on CPython and some packaging related questions, I also took the opportunity to catch up with the Mailman 3 developers - the open source world needs an email/web forum gateway that at least isn't actively awful, and the combination of Mailman 3 with the hyperkitty archiver is shaping up to be positively wonderful.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I didn't spend the &lt;i&gt;entire&lt;/i&gt; conference weekend talking to people - I actually got to go see a few talks as well. All of the talks I attended were excellent, but some particular personal highlights were &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/88/"&gt;Mike Bayer's deep dive&lt;/a&gt; into SQL Alchemy's session behaviour, &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/104/"&gt;the panel on&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href="http://bostonpythonworkshop.com/"&gt;Boston Python Workshop&lt;/a&gt; and a number of other BPW inspired education and outreach events, &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/98/"&gt;Mel Chua's whirlwind tour&lt;/a&gt; of educational psychology,  &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/144/"&gt;Lynn Root's educational projects&lt;/a&gt; for new coders (with &lt;a href="http://newcoder.io/"&gt;accompanying website&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/95/"&gt;Dave Malcolm's follow-up&lt;/a&gt; on his efforts with static analysis of all of the CPython extensions in Fedora, and &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/presentation/222/"&gt;Dave Beazley's ventures&lt;/a&gt; into automated home manufacturing of wooden toys (and destruction of laptop hard drives). There were plenty of other talks that looked interesting but I unfortunately didn't get to (one of the few downsides of having so many impromptu hallway conversations). All the PyCon US 2013 talks should be showing up on &lt;a href="http://www.pyvideo.org/category/33/pycon-us-2013"&gt;pyvideo.org&lt;/a&gt; as the presenters give the thumbs up, and the &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/pyconslides/"&gt;presentation slides&lt;/a&gt; are also available, so it's worth trawling through the respective lists for the topics that interest you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the midst of all that, Van Lindberg (PSF chairman) revealed the first public draft of the &lt;a href="http://preview.python.org/"&gt;redesigned python.org&lt;/a&gt; (I was one of the members of the review committee that selected Project Evolution, RevSys and Divio as the drivers of this initial phase of the redesign process), and also announced the &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2013/03/python-wins-trademark-dispute-rival-stops-calling-itself-python/"&gt;successful resolution&lt;/a&gt; of the PSF's trademark dispute in the EU.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This was only my second PyCon in North America (I've been to all three Australian PyCons, and attended PyCon India last year) and the first since I joined Red Hat. Meeting old friends from around the world, meeting other Pythonistas that I only knew by reputation or through Twitter and email, and meeting fellow Red Hatters that I had previously only met through IRC and email was a huge amount of fun. Attending the PyLadies charity auction, visiting the Computer History Museum with Guido van Rossum, Ned Deily and Dwayne Litzenberger (from Dropbox), chatting with Stephen Turnbull about promoting the adoption of open source and open source development practices in Japan, and getting to tour a small part of the Googleplex were just a few of the interesting bonus events from the week (and now I have a few days vacation to do the full tourist thing here in SFO).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm still on an adrenaline high, and there are at least a dozen different reasons why. If everything above isn't enough, there were a few other exciting developments happening behind the scenes that I can't go into yet. Fortunately, the details of those should become public over the next few weeks so I won't need to contain myself too long.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This week was intense, but &lt;i&gt;awesome&lt;/i&gt;. All the organisers, volunteers and sponsors that played a part in bringing it together should be proud :)&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2013/03/change-future-one-small-slice-of-pycon.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 01:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>