<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency (python)</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/categories/cat_python.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 22:22:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Inaugural PyCon Australia Education Miniconf</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/04/pycon-australia-education-miniconf.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;PyCon Australia launched its &lt;a href="http://2015.pycon-au.org/cfp"&gt;Call for Papers&lt;/a&gt; just over a month ago, and it closes in a little over a week on Friday the 8th of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new addition to PyCon Australia this year, and one I'm particularly excited about co-organising following Dr James Curran's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iVv7fCwVbp4&amp;amp;list=PLs4CJRBY5F1JQV44fKjRwjnh3CSTyJvOH&amp;amp;index=2"&gt;"Python for Every Child in Australia"&lt;/a&gt; keynote last year, is the inaugural Python in Education miniconf as a 4th specialist track on the Friday of the conference, before we move into the main program over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the CFP announcement: &lt;em&gt;"The Python in Education Miniconf aims to bring together community workshop organisers, professional Python instructors and professional educators across primary, secondary and tertiary levels to share their experiences and requirements, and identify areas of potential collaboration with each other and also with the broader Python community."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds like you, then I'd love to invite you to head over to the conference website and make your submission to the &lt;a href="http://2015.pycon-au.org/cfp"&gt;Call for Papers&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, all 4 miniconfs (Education, Science &amp;amp; Data Analysis, OpenStack and DjangoCon AU) are running our calls for proposals as part of the main conference CFP - every proposal submitted will be considered for both the main conference and the miniconfs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also pleased to announce two pre-arranged sessions at the Education Miniconf:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carrie Anne Philbin, author of &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/carrie-anne-philbins-adventures-in-raspberry-pi/"&gt;"Adventures in Raspberry Pi"&lt;/a&gt; and Education Pioneer at the Raspberry Pi Foundation will be speaking on the Foundation's &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/picademy/"&gt;Picademy&lt;/a&gt; professional development program for primary and secondary teachers &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Whitehouse, author of &lt;a href="http://www.wonko.info/ipt/"&gt;IPT - a virtual approach&lt;/a&gt; (online since 1992!) and a longstanding board member of the &lt;a href="https://www.qsite.edu.au/home"&gt;Queensland Society for Information Technology in Education&lt;/a&gt; will provide insight into some of the challenges and opportunities of integrating Python and other open source software into Australian IT education&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm genuinely looking forward to chairing this event, as I see tremendous potential in forging stronger connections between Australian educators (both formal and informal) and the broader Python and open source communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/04/pycon-australia-education-miniconf.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 10:43:14 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>