<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency (metablogging)</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 16:37:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The title of this blog</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/07/the-title-of-this-blog.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/06/30/the-busy-trap/"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; in praise of taking the time for idleness does a good job of articulating some of the reasons behind the title of this blog. I'm very jealous of my idle time - I &lt;i&gt;don't like it&lt;/i&gt; when I have things planned in advance night after night, week after week. I want my downtime to just do whatever seems interesting at the time, and I don't function well if I find it necessary to go without it for an extended period.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Being bored and being lazy are widely seen as things to be avoided. However, it all depends on how you look at them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Boredom is largely a sign of incredible &lt;i&gt;luxury&lt;/i&gt; - a time when the world is placing no immediate demands on us, so we have to come up with some means of satisfying our innate desire to be &lt;i&gt;doing something&lt;/i&gt;. Being bored means we're not busy obtaining food, or water, or shelter, or defending ourselves (or our food/water/shelter) from attackers, or otherwise pursuing the basic necessities of survival. It's an opportunity to play - maybe to explore (and change!) the world around us, maybe to explore fictional worlds created by others, maybe to create fictional worlds of our own, or to teach others about the real world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The negative view on being lazy often rests on unstated assumptions (even fears) about the &lt;i&gt;purpose&lt;/i&gt; of life: "Make more of yourself!", "Do something with your life!", "Leave your mark on the world!". When you get right down to it though, nobody (and I mean nobody) knows the meaning of life. We don't really know why it's better to get out of bed each morning and face the world - we just choose to believe that life is better than non-life, and engaging with the world is better than ignoring it. We create all sorts of stories we tell ourselves to justify our reasons for rejecting nihilism (to the point of killing each other over our choice of stories), but it ultimately comes down to a decision that the only life we know we have is this one, so we may as well do what can to try and enjoy it while we're here. Once we make that decision, and our basic survival needs are taken care of, everything beyond that point is optional and what we pursue will depend on what we're taught to perceive as valuable.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you look at the developed world, massive sections of it are aimed at giving people something to do when they're bored because their basic survival needs are taken care of more efficiently than they are by subsistence farming or hunter-gathering. This idle time may be spent creating new things, or consuming those things previously created by others. Some people see efficiency gains as a way to do more work in the same amount of time, but it's equally possible to exploit those gains to do the same amount of work in less time, leaving more time to be idle, and hence bored, and hence looking for other things to do. Is the former choice always better than the latter lazy choice? I don't believe so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Retreating from the deep philosophical questions and getting back to the more mundane question of the blog title, I do own another domain that redirects to this one, and thus have occasionally tinkered with the idea of rebranding the site as &lt;a href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/"&gt;Curious Efficiency&lt;/a&gt;. This would put a more traditionally "positive" spin on the concepts of idle investigation and elimination of unnecessary work mentioned in the blurb. However, I find the questions raised by the negative forms more intriguing though, and thus the current title remains. That said, if I ever get around to using my own domain for my primary email address, it will definitely be curiousefficiency rather than boredomandlaziness :)</description><category>metablogging</category><category>philosophy</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/07/the-title-of-this-blog.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 03:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sharing vs broadcasting</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/07/sharing-vs-broadcasting.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Even since I started playing with Google+ and its Circle mechanic, I've been trying to figure out why I don't like it. I thought it sounded great when I heard about it, but as soon as I started using it... meh :P&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I still haven't quite figured it out (although I mostly think it's the neither-chicken-nor-fowl aspect, along with it adding back ~500 useless "suggestions" from random Python mailing list contacts that I had already purged once), but it's certainly helped me see the way I communicate online in a different light.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For a long time, my only real online presence was regular postings to Python mailing lists, commenting on various sites and the very occasional post here on B&amp;amp;L.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After enough of my friends joined, Facebook was added to the mix, but I do everything I can to keep that locked down so only acquaintances can see most things I post there.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After going to PyconAU last year, and in the leadup to PyCon US earlier this year, I started up my @ncoghlan_dev account on Twitter, got the "python" category tag on here added to Planet Python, and started to develop a bit more of an online public presence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here on the blog, I can, and do, tag each post according to areas of interest. As far as I know, the 'python' tag is the only one with any significant readership (due to the aggregation via Planet Python), but people could subscribe to the philosophy or metablogging tags if they really wanted to.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When it comes to sharing information about myself, there's really only a few levels based on how much I trust the people involved: Friends&amp;amp;Family, Acquaintances, General Public pretty much covers it. Currently I handle that via a locked down FB for Friends, Family &amp;amp; Acquaintances (with a "Limited Access" list for people that I exclude from some things, like tagged photos) and completely public material on Twitter and Blogger.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The public stuff is mostly Python related, since that's my main online presence, but I'm fairly open about political and philosophical matters as well. FB, by contrast, rarely sees any mention of Python at all (and I'm often a little more restrained on the political and philosophical front).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Where I think Circles goes wrong is that it conflates &lt;i&gt;Access Control&lt;/i&gt; with &lt;i&gt;Topic Tagging&lt;/i&gt;. When I publish Python stuff, I'm quite happy for it to be public. However, I'd also be happy to tag it with "python", just as I do here on the blog, to make it easier for my friends to decide which of my updates they want to see.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is classic Publish/Subscribe architecture thinking. When Publishing, I normally want to be able to decide who *can* access stuff. That is limited by closeness, but typically unrelated to the topic. Having, tagging as a service to my subscribers, I am quite happy to do. When Subscribing, I want to be able to filter by topic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If I publish something to, say, my Pythonistas circle, than that does more than I want. Yes, it publishes it to them, but it also locks out everybody else. The ways I know people and the degree to which I trust them do not align well with the topics I like to talk about. I've already seen quite a few cases where the reshared versions of public statuses I have received have been limited access.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The more I think about it, the more I think I'm going to stick with my current policy of using it as a public micro-blog and pretty much ignore the fact that the Circles page exists.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/07/sharing-vs-broadcasting.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 17:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Posting code and syntax highlighting</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/posting-code-and-syntax-highlighting.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Before publishing the previous post, I looked into recommendations for syntax highlighting in coding-oriented blogs. In a quick search, syntaxhighlighter showed up repeatedly as the preferred choice, so that's what I went with.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It looks like I'm not the only one &lt;a href="http://www.knowthytools.com/2010/03/blogging-with-restructuredtext-and.html"&gt;that isn't entirely happy with that solution&lt;/a&gt; (although by using the "pre" tags rather than "script", my code should at least appear in the RSS feed).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Working with ReST would certainly be easier than the semi-HTML I'm currently using. Still, I think I have plenty to learn about Blogger's formatting tools before I abandon them entirely in favour of preformatted posts (which have their own drawbacks).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/posting-code-and-syntax-highlighting.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2011 09:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bye-bye Blogilo</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/bye-bye-blogilo.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;OK, when a blogging app can't figure out my blog identity automatically and crashes every time I submit a post (but after submitting the post to blogger), 'tis clearly not the app for me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm just happy the first 3 posts didn't properly include the 'python' tag either, so at least Planet Python shouldn't have been spammed with any noise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Back to the in-browser editor for now...&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/bye-bye-blogilo.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 13:29:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Linking sites in blog posts</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/linking-sites-in-blog-posts.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Call me paranoid, but the idea of trusting a blogging app with my Google account details really doesn't appeal to me. So, "BlogThis!" on the links bar it is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would be nice if BlogThis! popped up the full Blogger editor instead of a partial one (missing features like editing the post tags), but using it to save pre-linked drafts should be more than adequate for those occasions when I'm commenting on a link rather than writing something from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Test: editing an existing post...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/02/linking-sites-in-blog-posts.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Comments update and site to-do list</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/01/comments-update-and-site-to-do-list.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Having used DISQUS elsewhere as a commenter and not being a great fan of the default Blogger comment system, I've configured the blog to use DISQUS instead.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I've also asked to have the blog's python related posts added to the Planet Python feed, so we'll see how that pans out.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The main thing I'm still not entirely happy with is the site colour scheme - while I'm still a fan of the whole light-text-on-dark-background style, the contrast between clicked links and the current black background really isn't significant enough. I'll probably tinker with that a bit over the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/01/comments-update-and-site-to-do-list.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 12:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Joining the modern era of blogging</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2010/12/joining-modern-era-of-blogging.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, that template was old. OK, brushed the dust out of the corners (i.e. switched to the modern Blogger template engine and away from the old crappy one) and correctly configured the domain delegation for the www.boredomandlaziness.org address.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Once the DNS updates filter through the intarwebs, I'll reconfigure Blogger to use that address instead of the default one.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2010/12/joining-modern-era-of-blogging.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 13:29:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Email Blogging</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2004/12/email-blogging.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Just checking it works. Nothing to see here. Move along.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-- &lt;br&gt;Nick Coghlan   |   ncoghlan@email.com   |   Brisbane, Australia&lt;br&gt;---------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br&gt;             http://boredomandlaziness.skystorm.net&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2004/12/email-blogging.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2004 09:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Firing it up</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2004/11/firing-it-up.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So, I occasionally post stuff over at &lt;a href="http://www.talkinboutstuff.net" target="_top"&gt;Talkinboutstuff&lt;/a&gt;. However, that's mostly for random crap I expect the rest of the guys to find interesting/annoying/whatever.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;So, I created this extra blog for myself - somewhere to pontificate about things I &lt;i&gt;don't&lt;/i&gt; expect them to find interesting, like software and Python and open source and what have you. And, anything of interest to them can be cross-linked quite happily :)
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Maybe I'll even get around to attaching this thing to a real domain name!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>metablogging</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2004/11/firing-it-up.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2004 12:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>