<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency (Posts about philosophy)</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.curiousefficiency.org/categories/philosophy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 11:44:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Seven billion seconds per second</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, YouTube put together their
&lt;a href="https://www.onehourpersecond.com/"&gt;"One hour per second"&lt;/a&gt; site, visualising
the fact that for every second of time that elapses, an hour of video is
uploaded to YouTube. Their
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/yt/press/statistics.html"&gt;current statistics page&lt;/a&gt;
indicates that figure is now up to 100 hours per minute (about 1.7 hours per
second).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressive numbers to be sure. However, there's another set of numbers I
personally consider significantly more impressive: every second, more than
seven billion seconds are added to the tally of collective human existence
on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about that for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 7 billion seconds of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 117 million minutes of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 2 million hours of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 81 thousand days of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 11 thousand weeks of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 222 years of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience, every single second, of every
single day. And as the world population grows, it's only going to get faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience per second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 centuries per minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;801 centuries per hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 millenia per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;135 millenia per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 billion years per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth in our collective human experience over the course of a single
year would stretch halfway back to the dawn of time if it was experienced
by an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We currently squander most of that potential. We allow a lot of it to be
wasted scrabbling for the basic means of survival like food, clean water and
shelter. We lock knowledge up behind closed doors, forcing people to reinvent
solutions to already solved problems because they can't afford the entry fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ascribe value to people based solely on their success in the resource
acquisition game that is the market economy, without acknowledging the large
degree to which sheer random chance is frequently the determinant in who wins
and who loses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We inflict bile and hate on people who have the temerity to say "I'm here,
I'm human, and I have a right to be heard", while being different from us.
We often focus on those superficial differences, rather than our underlying
common humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fight turf wars based on where we were born, the colour of our skin, and
which supernatural beings or economic doctrines we allow to guide our
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to change this? Is it possible to build a world where we
consider people to have inherent value &lt;em&gt;just because they're fellow
humans&lt;/em&gt;, rather than because of specific things they have done, or specific
roles they take up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly don't know, but it seems worthwhile to try. I certainly find it
hard to conceive of a better possible way to spend my own meagre slice of
those seven billion seconds per second :)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 07:35:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Wielding Power</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making the usually implied disclaimer completely explicit on this one:
the views expressed in this article are my own, and do not necessarily
reflect the position of any organisations of which I am a member.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power is an interesting thing, and something that, as a society at large
(rather than the specialists that spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time thinking about it),
we really don't spend enough time giving serious consideration to. Trust and
fear, hope and despair, interwoven with the complex dynamics of
interpersonal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious kind of power is based on fear: people listening when you
tell them what to do, based on a fear of the consequences if they ignore
you. Many corporations have traditionally operated on this model: do what
you're told, or you'll be fired. "You might lose your job" then hangs as
an implicit threat behind every interaction with your management chain,
and a complex web of legal obligations and social safety nets has arisen
(to a greater or lesser degree in different countries) to help manage the
effectiveness of this threat and redress the power imbalance. Fear based
power is also, ultimately, the kind of power embodied in the legal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not the only kind of power though, and this post is largely about
another form of it: power based on &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Power based on trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear based power can be transferred fairly effectively: disobeying a
delegate can be punished as severely as disobeying the original authority
and so it goes. Interpersonal considerations don't get much consideration
in such environments - they're about getting the job done, without any real
concern for the feelings of the people doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency of that kind of centralised control degrades fairly quickly
though - with everyone being in constant fear of punishment, a whole lot
of effort ends up being expended on figuring out what the orders are,
communicating the orders, ensuring the orders have been followed, requesting
new orders when the situation changes, recording exactly what was done to
implement the orders and ensuring that if anything goes wrong it was the
original orders that were to blame rather than the people following them
and so on and so forth. It's like a human body that has no local reflexes,
but instead has to think through the idea of removing its hand from a
hotplate as an act of deliberate will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a different kind of power though, summed up well in this &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc"&gt;YouTube
video&lt;/a&gt;. What that kind of
power is based on is the idea that once people have their core survival
needs met, there are three key motivators that often work better than money:
autonomy, mastery and purpose. (Note: this is &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; core survival needs
are met. If people are still stressed about food, shelter, their health and
their personal relationships, then autonomy, mastery and purpose can go take
a hike)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its best, an environment based on autonomy, mastery and purpose is one
of mutual trust and respect. The purpose of the overall organisation and
its individual components is sufficiently well articulated that everyone
involved understands their responsibilities and how their efforts contribute
to the greater whole, individuals are given a high degree of autonomy in
determining how best to meet their obligations, and are supported in the
pursuit of the required mastery to fulfil those obligations as well as
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of distributed trust that Silicon Valley &lt;em&gt;tries&lt;/em&gt; to sum up
in its "move fast and break things" motto, but fails miserably in doing so.
The reason? Those last two words there: "break things". It's an
incredibly technocratic view of the world, and one that leaves out the
most important element of any situation: the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a key point many technologists miss: ultimately, &lt;em&gt;technology doesn't
matter&lt;/em&gt;. It is not an end unto itself - it is only ever a means to an end,
and that end will almost always be something related to people (we humans
are an egocentric bunch). When you "break things" you &lt;em&gt;hurt people&lt;/em&gt;, directly
or indirectly. Now, maybe those things needed to be broken (and a lot of
them do). Maybe those things were already hurting people, and the change
just shifts (and hopefully lessens) the burden. But the specific phrasing
in the Silicon Valley motto is one of cavalier irresponsibility, of freedom
from consequences. "Don't think about the people that may be hurt by your
actions - just move fast and break things, that's what we do here!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is NOT OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it needs to be OK to break things, whether deliberately or by mistake.
Without that, "autonomy" becomes a myth, and we are left with stagnation.
However, there's a difference between doing so carelessly, without
accounting for the impact on those that may be harmed by the chosen course
of action, and doing so while taking full responsibility for the harm your
actions may have caused .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, it's time to shift topics a bit. I assure you they're actually
related, which may become clearer further down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a corporation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The glib answer here would be "a toxic cesspool of humanity", and I'll grant
that's a fair description of a lot of them (see the earlier observations
regarding fear based power). I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; a capitalist though (albeit one that is
strongly in favour of redistributive tax systems), so I see more potential
for good in them than many other folks do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm going to give my perspective on the way some of the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt; ones
work when running smoothly, at least in regards to three roles: the Chief
Financial Officer, the Chief Technology Officer and the Chief Executive
Officer. (You may choose not to believe me when I say non-toxic corporations
are a real thing, but I assure you, such companies &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; exist, as most
people &lt;em&gt;don't actually like&lt;/em&gt; working for toxic cesspools of humanity. It's
just that fully avoiding the descent into toxicity as organisations grow is,
as yet, an unsolved problem in society. Radical transparency does seem to
help a lot, though. Something about the cleansing power of sunlight and
competing centres of power...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-toxic CFO role is pretty straightforward: their job is to make sure
that everyone gets paid, and the company not only survives, but thrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-toxic CTO role is also pretty straightforward: they're the ultimate
authority on the technological foundations of an organisation. What's on the
horizon that they need to be aware of? What's growing old and needs to be
phased out in favour of something more recent? What just needs a bit of
additional investment to bring it up to scratch?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of a CEO is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; less clear. "Finance" is pretty clear, as is
"Technology". But what does "Executive" mean? They're not just in charge
of the executives - they're in charge of the whole company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take on it? The CEO is ultimately the "keeper of the company culture".
They ultimately decide not only &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; gets done, but also &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it gets
done. While they have a lot of other important responsibilities, a key one in
my mind is that it is the CEO's job to make sure that both the CFO and CTO
remember to account for the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; that will ultimately be tasked with
handling "execution". They're the ones that say "no, we're not cutting
that, it's important to the way we operate - we need to find another way
to save money" (remember, we're only talking about the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt;
corporations here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when employees of a corporation expect that company to do the right
thing by them? They're trusting the CEO. Not the CFO. Not the CTO. The &lt;em&gt;CEO&lt;/em&gt;.
Arguably the key defining characteristic of a non-toxic corporation is that
the CEO is &lt;em&gt;worthy&lt;/em&gt; of that trust, as they will not only make those
commitments to their employees, but also put the mechanisms in place
to ensure the commitments are actually met. (This doesn't require any
kind-hearted altruism on the CEO's part, by the way. You can get the same
outcome through hard-nosed capitalism since making honest commitments to
your staff and then &lt;em&gt;keeping them&lt;/em&gt; is  what "our people are our greatest
asset" actually looks like in practice - it's just that a lot of
organisations that &lt;em&gt;say&lt;/em&gt; that don't actually &lt;em&gt;mean it&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commenting on other people's business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that brings us to the specific reason I sat down to write this article: a
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450396296289869825"&gt;tweet I posted&lt;/a&gt;
earlier today regarding Mozilla's public debate over the board's choice of
CEO. Specifically, I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would take Eich accepting the Mozilla CEO role to mean his personal
pride matters more to him than Mozilla's mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a pretty bold statement to make about someone I don't know and have
never even met, and in relation to an organisation that I don't have any
direct relationship with beyond being a user of their software and a fan
of their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the things I didn't suggest. I didn't suggest he resign from his
existing position as CTO. I didn't suggest that the Mozilla board withdraw
their offer of the CEO position. However, I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; state that, from my
perspective as an outsider that wants to see Mozilla execute on their
mission to the best of their ability, "trust me" is a sufficiently big call
to have to make for a role as critical as the CEO position that I don't
believe Eich should be asking that of his fellow members of the Mozilla
community. Actions have consequences, and one of those consequences can be
"No, you no longer have the right to request our trust - you actively hurt
us, and we don't believe you when you say you wish to make amends".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Eich's credit, he at least didn't just say "trust me", but rather made a
number of
&lt;a href="https://brendaneich.com/2014/03/inclusiveness-at-mozilla/"&gt;specific commitments&lt;/a&gt;.
However, the time to build that credibility in a relatively open organisation
is &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; accepting such a significant role, not after. Otherwise, there
will always be a lingering doubt for affected individuals that any public
statements are a matter of the responsibilities of the position, rather than
a genuine change in personal convictions. When it comes to matters like a
commitment to inclusiveness you &lt;em&gt;don't want&lt;/em&gt; a CEO that is going through
the motions out of a sense of obligation: this stuff is hard work and
tempting to skimp on, even when you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; care about it at a personal level
(as a case in point - it would have been &lt;em&gt;so much easier&lt;/em&gt; for me to not
comment on this situation at all, that I almost left it at just a couple
of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450381744227643392"&gt;vague&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450382065800728576"&gt;allusions&lt;/a&gt;
on Twitter rather than getting specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separating the personal from the professional is always difficult, and
few places moreso than the CEO role. During my tenure at Boeing, we had two
CEOs asked to resign due to unprofessional conduct. The military industrial
complex is a sordid mire of duplicitous misbehaviour and waste that makes
the open source technology community look like saints by comparison (and
I'll let you draw your own conclusions as to what it says about me
personally that I survived there for more than a decade), yet even they
were of the opinion that personal conduct &lt;em&gt;matters&lt;/em&gt; at the CEO level,
even moreso than in other less prominent roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, I personally do hope Eich's newfound commitment to
inclusiveness is genuine, and that the concerns raised regarding his
appointment as CEO prove to be unfounded. I'd prefer to live in a world
where the blog post linked above represents a genuine change of heart,
rather than being merely a tactical consideration to appease particular
groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, my opinion on this topic doesn't matter - it's now up to
Eich to demonstrate through his actions that he's worthy of the trust that
the Mozilla board have placed in him, and for concerned members of the
Mozilla community to decide whether they're willing to adopt a "wait and
see" approach as suggested, or if they consider that belated request in and
of itself to be an unacceptable breach of &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; trust.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The title of this blog</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/07/the-title-of-this-blog/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/06/30/the-busy-trap/"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; in praise of taking the time for idleness does a good job of articulating some of the reasons behind the title of this blog. I'm very jealous of my idle time - I &lt;i&gt;don't like it&lt;/i&gt; when I have things planned in advance night after night, week after week. I want my downtime to just do whatever seems interesting at the time, and I don't function well if I find it necessary to go without it for an extended period.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Being bored and being lazy are widely seen as things to be avoided. However, it all depends on how you look at them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Boredom is largely a sign of incredible &lt;i&gt;luxury&lt;/i&gt; - a time when the world is placing no immediate demands on us, so we have to come up with some means of satisfying our innate desire to be &lt;i&gt;doing something&lt;/i&gt;. Being bored means we're not busy obtaining food, or water, or shelter, or defending ourselves (or our food/water/shelter) from attackers, or otherwise pursuing the basic necessities of survival. It's an opportunity to play - maybe to explore (and change!) the world around us, maybe to explore fictional worlds created by others, maybe to create fictional worlds of our own, or to teach others about the real world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The negative view on being lazy often rests on unstated assumptions (even fears) about the &lt;i&gt;purpose&lt;/i&gt; of life: "Make more of yourself!", "Do something with your life!", "Leave your mark on the world!". When you get right down to it though, nobody (and I mean nobody) knows the meaning of life. We don't really know why it's better to get out of bed each morning and face the world - we just choose to believe that life is better than non-life, and engaging with the world is better than ignoring it. We create all sorts of stories we tell ourselves to justify our reasons for rejecting nihilism (to the point of killing each other over our choice of stories), but it ultimately comes down to a decision that the only life we know we have is this one, so we may as well do what can to try and enjoy it while we're here. Once we make that decision, and our basic survival needs are taken care of, everything beyond that point is optional and what we pursue will depend on what we're taught to perceive as valuable.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you look at the developed world, massive sections of it are aimed at giving people something to do when they're bored because their basic survival needs are taken care of more efficiently than they are by subsistence farming or hunter-gathering. This idle time may be spent creating new things, or consuming those things previously created by others. Some people see efficiency gains as a way to do more work in the same amount of time, but it's equally possible to exploit those gains to do the same amount of work in less time, leaving more time to be idle, and hence bored, and hence looking for other things to do. Is the former choice always better than the latter lazy choice? I don't believe so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Retreating from the deep philosophical questions and getting back to the more mundane question of the blog title, I do own another domain that redirects to this one, and thus have occasionally tinkered with the idea of rebranding the site as &lt;a href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/"&gt;Curious Efficiency&lt;/a&gt;. This would put a more traditionally "positive" spin on the concepts of idle investigation and elimination of unnecessary work mentioned in the blurb. However, I find the questions raised by the negative forms more intriguing though, and thus the current title remains. That said, if I ever get around to using my own domain for my primary email address, it will definitely be curiousefficiency rather than boredomandlaziness :)</description><category>metablogging</category><category>philosophy</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/07/the-title-of-this-blog/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 03:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Effective communication, brain hacking and diversity</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/07/effective-communication-brain-hacking/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jessenoller"&gt;Jesse Noller&lt;/a&gt; recently posted an interesting quote on Twitter:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"One who feels hurt while listening to harsh language may lose his mindfulness and not hear what the other person is really saying."&lt;/blockquote&gt;When you think about it, human language is a truly awe inspiring tool. By the simple act of creating certain vibrations in the air, marks on a page or electromagnetic patterns in a storage system, we're able to project our thoughts and feelings across space and time, using them to shape the thoughts and feelings of others.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;While this ability to communicate is so thoroughly natural to most of us as humans that we typically take it for granted, it is actually an amazing world shaping capability &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J7E-aoXLZGY"&gt;deserving of our respect and attention&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And once we start giving it the attention it deserves, then we realise that we can judge the &lt;i&gt;effectiveness&lt;/i&gt; of our own communication by looking at the communication that is subsequently reflected back at us. How well do those reflections mirror the thoughts and feelings that our own words were intended to create? It's the linguistic equivalent of running our code and seeing if it does what we wanted it to do.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All communication is a form of brain hacking, even when the only target is ourselves. We write lists of goals - formulating for our own benefit concrete plans of action that we can then tackle one step at a time. We write polemics, trying to engender in others some dim sense of the joy or outrage we feel with respect to certain topics. Sometimes we succeed, sometimes we fail. Sometimes we assume certain shared beliefs and understanding, so the point completely fails to come across to those without that common background.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For those closest to us, those with the most shared history, we have a rich tapestry of common knowledge to draw from. Movies we've all seen, books we've all read, events we all attended, discussions we were all part of - outsiders attempting to follow a transcript of our conversations would likely soon be utterly lost due to the shared subtext that isn't explicitly articulated (and the same is true for any group of close friends).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As groups get larger, the amount of truly common knowledge decreases, but there's still plenty of unwritten subtext that backs up whatever is explicitly articulated. In a certain sense, that unwritten subtext can be seen as the very &lt;i&gt;definition&lt;/i&gt; of culture - it's the things you don't have to say because they're assumed. My past &lt;a href="https://www.curiousefficiency.org/2011/04/musings-on-culture-of-python-dev.html"&gt;musings on the culture of python-dev&lt;/a&gt; are an example of this.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And that brings us to the point of considering the opening quote, diversity and questions of common courtesy. When speaking to friends, I can share truly awful jokes without offence because of the shared background information as to what is and isn't acceptable (and what things should be taken seriously). As the group being addressed gets larger, then the valid assumptions I can make about shared views of the world become fewer and fewer, so I have to start explicitly articulating things I would otherwise assume, and simply not say some things because I know (or at least strongly suspect) that they won't come across correctly to the audience I'm attempting to reach. Sometimes even addressing similar groups of people in a different context can change the assumptions as to what is a reasonable way to phrase things.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If a member of my target audience gets hung up on my wording or my choice of examples to the point where they miss the underlying message, then to a large degree, the responsibility lies with &lt;i&gt;me&lt;/i&gt; as the originator of the communication. Now, I'm not a saint and make no pretence of being one. The rich fields of metaphors in English include many relating to subjects that are truly quite horrific or otherwise offensive to various groups of people. Sometimes I'm going to use that kind of phrasing without thinking about it, especially when talking rather than writing (my own &lt;a href="http://www.mit.edu/~jcb/tact.html"&gt;innate tact filter&lt;/a&gt; is definitely set up to filter incoming communication, so applying tact in the outwards direction is a conscious process rather than something I do automatically). If such a miscommunication happens and someone points it out, then the onus is on me to admit that yes, my choice of words was poor and obscured my meaning rather than illuminating it. That's life, I make mistakes, and hopefully we can move on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not entirely a one way street, though. Just as we apply contextual analysis to our understanding of historical writings, so it can be useful to apply the same approach to things that are said by &lt;i&gt;current&lt;/i&gt; figures. Richard Dawkins recently made some ill-advised comments in relation to &lt;a href="http://skepchick.org"&gt;Skepchick's&lt;/a&gt; advice to men to avoid certain actions that make them look creepy (that's all she said, "Don't do this, it's creepy" and she copped flack for it, as if she'd said people doing it should be sent to prison or castrated or something equally extreme). Does the fact that Dawkins clearly didn't get why he was &lt;a href="http://skepchick.org/2011/07/dear-richard-dawkins/"&gt;in the wrong&lt;/a&gt; make him a horrible human being or devalue his extensive contributions to our understanding of evolutionary biology*? No, it doesn't, any more than Isaac Newton's obsession with alchemy devalued his contributions to physics and mathematics. It just makes him a product of the culture that raised him. Hopefully he'll eventually realise this and publicly apologise for failing to give the matter due consideration before weighing in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, what really surprised me is the number of people that indicate they're &lt;i&gt;shocked&lt;/i&gt; by his words, or questioning their support for his other activities just because he so vividly demonstrated his cluelessness on this particular topic. The world is a complicated place and the social dynamics of privilege, cultural blindspots and effectively encouraging diversity aren't one of the easiest pieces to comprehend. Hell, as a middle-class, 30-something, white, English-speaking, straight, cisgendered male living in Australia I'm quite certain that my own grasp of the topic is heavily coloured by the fact that on pretty much &lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt; of the typical grounds for discrimination I'm in the favoured majority (being an atheist is arguably the only exception, but that's far less of a problem here in Australia than it is in the US. Our Prime Minister is an acknowledged atheist and even the Murdoch media machine didn't really try to make much of an issue out of that before the last election). I do my best to understand the topic of diversity based on the experiences of those that actually have to deal with it on a daily basis, but it's still a far cry from seeing things first hand.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, since I don't believe I can speak credibly to the topic of diversity directly, I instead prefer to encourage people to reflect on the value and nature of communication and community in general. Martin Fowler &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/SmutOnRails.html"&gt;wrote an excellent piece&lt;/a&gt; about the challenge of creating communities that are welcoming to a diverse audience without rendering them bland and humourless (as the &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Theories_of_humor#Benign_Violation_Theory"&gt;benign violations&lt;/a&gt; of expectations and assumptions that are at the heart of most humour often depend on the shared context that welcoming communities can't necessarily assume). This &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b0Ti-gkJiXc"&gt;excellent video&lt;/a&gt; highlights the importance of focusing on &lt;i&gt;actions&lt;/i&gt; (e.g. "This thing you said was inappropriate and you should consider apologising for saying it") rather than &lt;i&gt;attributes&lt;/i&gt; (e.g. "You are a racist/misogynist/whatever"). If the latter is actually true, you're unlikely to change their mind and if it *isn't* true, you're likely to miss an opportunity to educate them as they get defensive and stop listening (refer back to that opening quote!).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I don't pretend to have all (or even any of) the answers, I just believe the entire topic of effective communication and all it entails is one worthy of our collective consideration, since effective communication is almost always a necessary precursor to taking effective &lt;i&gt;action&lt;/i&gt; (e.g. on matters such as &lt;a href="https://www.curiousefficiency.org/2011/03/climate-change-skepticism-text-book.html"&gt;mitigating and coping with climate change&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In many respects though, the entire topic is really quite simple. To quote Abe Lincoln in one of my all time favourite movies:&lt;blockquote&gt;Be excellent to each other.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;----&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;* Seriously, read the popular science books on biology that Dawkins has written, especially "The Greatest Show on Earth". They're orders of magnitudes better than "The God Delusion", which is far too laden with angry and aggressive undertones to be an effective tool for communicating with anyone that doesn't already agree with the thesis of the book. In his biology books, his obvious love and passion for the subject matter comes to the fore and they're by far the better for it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note for Planet Python:&lt;/b&gt; even though this post is about communication rather than code, I have included the python tag since a couple of different diversity related issues have come up recently on python-dev and psf-members. It is no coincidence that "communication" and "community" share a common(!) root in "communis".&lt;/i&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><category>python</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/07/effective-communication-brain-hacking/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2011 07:10:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Climate change "skepticism": a text book case of the "Tragedy of the Commons"</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/climate-change-skepticism-text-book/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So, with the government moving to implement a carbon tax, the issue of climate change and attempts to mitigate it are once again a big deal here in Australia.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Inspired by a friend's comment comparing carbon taxes with fines for littering, along with a few of the  responses to that comment, I started pondering the similarities and differences between the current attempts to deal with carbon dioxide emissions, and the &lt;a href="http://www.edf.org/page.cfm?tagID=1085"&gt;effective cost internalisation schemes created&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990's that severely reduced industrial sulphur dioxide emissions, as well as various current laws that prohibit dumping of toxic waste in developed nations (and their &lt;a href="http://www.ehow.com/info_8012059_causes-dumping-third-world-countries.html"&gt;unintended side effects&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Fair warning before I wade in: I've simplified quite a few things, particularly on the acid rain front. This post is long enough as it is, without making it even longer with all the relevant caveats about other causes of acid rain and any other details I've glossed over as being irrelevant to the main point of the article. It's a general overview, not a peer reviewed scientific paper)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;A tale of two gases&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;The key similarity between sulphur dioxide induced acid rain and carbon dioxide induced global warming is hopefully fairly obvious: they both represent a classic economic "externality", a cost borne by someone other than the person responsible for causing it. The industries and individuals emitting these pollutants don't suffer any immediate harmful consequence through the normal action of nature.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In situations like that, regulation in one form or another is the only effective tool we have to ensure that at least some portion of those external costs is reflected back on the responsible individuals. As noted in the link above, this approach proved extraordinarily effective in reducing acid rain in the US, drastically cutting sulphur emissions at a fraction of the originally predicted cost.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, there are a few key differences that have contributed to the discussion over carbon dioxide taking a rather different path to that over sulphur dioxide:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's hard to deny the harmful effects of sulphur dioxide emissions when plants, fish and insects are dying due to the excessive levels of acidity in rain and ground water. By contrast, it is very hard to convey clearly why a small rise in average global temperatures is going to be such a bad thing, or even how human carbon dioxide emissions contribute to that happening.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Acid rain from sulphur emissions is generally a &lt;i&gt;local&lt;/i&gt; problem with local causes (from a continental perspective, anyway). Stop emitting sulphur dioxide in the US and acid rain stops falling in the US. Significantly reduce carbon dioxide emissions in Australia (or even the US) though, and we're likely still screwed if other countries don't follow suit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The "sulphur" cycle (how long it takes for the sulphur emissions to be deposited back on the ground as acid rain) is significantly shorter than that of carbon, so efforts to reduce emissions will have an effect on water acidity levels in a reasonably short time frame&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;Comparisons with anti-waste dumping laws are similar: the effects of toxic waste dumping are generally both local, obvious and able to be cleaned up within years rather than decades, so it is easy to get support for laws prohibiting such practices, even if the end result of those laws is just to export the problem to a poorer country.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Manufacturing doubt and exploiting the "Grey Fallacy"&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Acid rain is an easy problem to sell: the acid damages plants and objects directly, so the harm can be easily conveyed through pictures and videos. The problem of climate change, though is far, far harder to illustrate simply, since it is a signal buried in some very noisy weather patterns.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A fundamental issue is the fact that people don't really experience climate, but instead experience weather. The day to day and seasonal variations in the weather massively exceed the scale of the underlying trends being discussed by climate scientists. The fact that predicting the weather in a few days time is harder than predicting long term climate trends is actually massively counterintuitive, even though almost all scientists and engineers are familiar with the fact that random fluctuations at a small scale may average out to something almost perfectly predictable at a large scale (compare the unpredictable nature of quantum physics with the straightforward determinism of classical Newtonian mechanics).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We're also not really used to the idea of directly affecting the balance of the planet on a global scale. In absolute terms, the effects of the sun, the oceans and the plants on the carbon cycle all dwarf the human contribution. The idea that the non-human forcings were actually largely in balance with each other, and that the comparatively small human contribution is enough to tip that balance to the point of producing more carbon than can be absorbed by natural mechanisms is really quite a subtle one.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The scientific background needed to truly understand and come to grips with the hows and the whys of the IPCC predictions reminds me of &lt;a href="http://abstrusegoose.com/272"&gt;this comic&lt;/a&gt; regarding the knowledge needed to even begin to understand the vagaries of string theory (make sure to click through on the comic itself to see the whole chain of images).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If there wasn't anyone around with a vested interest in maintaining the status quo (at least for a while longer), this likely wouldn't be a problem. Scientists, politicians, economists and engineers could proceed with the development of mitigation strategies, while also attempting to educate the general populace as to the reasons behind any actions taken. Since such vested interests do exist, however, their opposition makes it significantly harder to convince the lay public that there is a real problem here.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Because climate science is such a complex topic, it is actually quite hard to explain to a non-scientist just &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; the scientific consensus is as strong as it is. If you oversimplify, you veer into territory where statements are so oversimplified that they border on being false. However, if you're coming from the other angle and want to persuade people that the science "isn't settled", then you're no longer constrained by the need to be accurate and can just go with whatever sounds more intuitively plausible and/or better caters to people's natural inclinations and prejudices.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sites like &lt;a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com/"&gt;Skeptical Science&lt;/a&gt; do their best to clearly explain why the oft-repeated "skeptic" arguments are basically BS (and do it well), but to someone only following the Cliff Notes mainstream media version of the debate, the temptation is still very, very strong to just assume the truth lies somewhere between the two positions being debated.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Telling people to "do their own research" doesn't really help all that much in practice. Telling the BS from the valid science is itself a fine art that takes a great deal of skill and experience. Being a veteran of arguments with creationists (and even intelligent design advocates) is actually quite beneficial, since the global warming "skeptics" use many of the same rhetorical tricks as creationists do when attempting to deny the fact of evolution (incessant use of such deceptive tactics is actually one of the major hints that someone is trying to sell you a line rather than just stating the truth as they see it). The most common tactic used by both groups is to drag out a thoroughly rebutted argument for each new audience, in hopes that they aren't aware of the existence of a rebuttal.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For example, just as most people can't answer "How could a bombardier beetle possibly evolve?" off the top of their heads - I've actually forgotten all of the plausible answers myself - neither can they answer questions like "If the climate is supposed to be warming, why is it colder now than it was during the Middle Ages?". While that one is actually fairly straightforward to answer (ice cores and other data shows that the medieval warming was likely localised to Europe due to various currents in the Atlantic, but this merely shifted heat around, so that other parts of the world were correspondingly colder), there are dozens of other oft-repeated thoroughly debunked arguments, and it's basically impossible for a mere interested observer to remember them all. As it turns out, I had actually misremembered the correct explanation for the Medieval warm period, so the point above isn't quite right and invites an attack on the grounds that I don't know what I'm what I'm talking about. To some extent that's actually true - my opinion on climate science issues is based on a meta-analysis of the trustworthiness of various information sources (including the full &lt;a href="http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_and_data_reports.shtml"&gt;IPCC reports&lt;/a&gt;), since I'm not inclined to spend a few decades studying up and redoing all the science myself. Fortunately, Skeptical Science has the &lt;a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com/medieval-warm-period.htm"&gt;full story&lt;/a&gt; for this question and many others (the MWP was actually colder than the latter half of this century, despite higher solar activity and lower volcanic activity), so correcting my error is the task of a few moments. And if you're still wondering about the bombardier beetle thing, TalkOrigins has the &lt;a href="http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/bombardier.html"&gt;full story for that&lt;/a&gt;, too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fortunately, at the decision making level here in Australia, this part of the debate seems to be coming to a close, with even Toby Abbott (the leader of the opposition) at least paying lip service to the fact that human-induced increases in average global temperatures are now a fact of life. However, the mainstream media is still happy to "teach the controversy" in the hopes of picking up a few more eyeballs (or ears) to sell to their advertisers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;But the problem is so much bigger than us!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, even once you get agreement that human-induced global warming due to excessive carbon dioxide emissions is a genuine problem, you then run into the "But we can't do anything about it!" attitude.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many Australians (including some elected members of our Federal parliament) go "Oh, but the US/Europe/Brazil/Russia/India/China have a much bigger impact than we do. Doing anything will hurt our international competitiveness without really achieving anything, so we shouldn't bother."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Even the higher emission countries point fingers at each other. The US won't budge until China does. The BRIC countries are waiting for the US to make a move, and use US inaction as justification for similarly doing nothing in the meantime.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An absolutely textbook "Tragedy of the Commons" reaction. And we know how that story ends, don't we? In the long run everybody loses, nobody wins.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How do you fix it? Rules, regulations and social pressure. The "community of nations" isn't just words. The complex web of interdependencies that spans the world gives countries real power to exert influence on each other. Once some countries start to make a move towards serious carbon emission control strategies, then that becomes a bargaining chip to use in international negotiations. Will it work? Who knows. The only thing we know for sure is that the more carbon we pump into the atmosphere over the next few decades, the higher the impact from global warming will be (it's now guaranteed that there will be &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; impact - the carbon cycle is too long for us to prevent that at this late stage of the game).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ideally you would want to adopt an emissions trading scheme along the lines of that used to curb sulfur emissions, but the wholehearted embrace of dodgy pseudoscience by far too many members of our Federal Opposition party spiked that particular barrel.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So a carbon tax it is (for now, anyway). The hysterical cries of "Oh my god, you've doomed the country!" ring loudly from those that will bear most of the direct costs of actually internalising the negative effects their carbon emissions have on the wider environment. Their motives are, to say the least, a little bit suspect. The political opportunism involved in our Federal Opposition leader backing them is disappointing, but unsurprising.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;In the PM's words&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's a nice summary of the current situation in a Fairfax &lt;a href="http://www.smh.com.au/opinion/politics/extreme-views-must-not-decide-carbon-tax-20110323-1c6ky.html"&gt;opinion piece&lt;/a&gt; that went out over Gillard's byline:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;The longer we leave it the harder action on climate change gets. This reform road is a hard one to walk. Just as doing nothing is not an option, we need to be careful to ensure that we do not make decisions that will cost our economy and jobs.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;There's a definite risk that the government's plans won't live up to their ambitions. However, the world's past experience with the sulfur dioxide doomsayers should arouse some deep skepticism and not directed towards those wanting to press forward with plans to curb carbon emissions.</description><category>philosophy</category><category>politics</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/climate-change-skepticism-text-book/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Which matters more to you: being right or staying friends?</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/01/which-matters-more-to-you-being-right/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Browsing through the &lt;a href="http://www.religioustolerance.org/"&gt;Religious Tolerance&lt;/a&gt; site, I felt inspired to turn my Ethos post into a Visitor Essay submission. I have no idea if they will ever post it (as it turns out, they did so quite promptly, &lt;a href="http://www.religioustolerance.org/coghlan01.htm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), but decided to put the whole thing up here (after the jump) regardless. &lt;br&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;The role of faith in my life has been a varied one. My parents are Roman Catholics (albeit ones with more than a few issues with the way the Church hierarchy run the show), and so I grew up doing the traditional Roman Catholic thing - convent primary school (although there were no teaching nuns by the time I came through) followed by a Christian Brothers high school (although again, one with mostly lay teachers). Church on Sunday was a weekly family ritual, and after drifting away into the typical agnosticism of the Australian teenager, I rediscovered my faith through the National Evangelisation Teams program. Enthused about my faith again, I started actually studying it - reading the Bible, looking at church teachings, that kind of thing. But something strange happened - the more I studied, the more hollow it all seemed. I *didn't* agree with everything the Bible said, or everything the Church taught, and neither did my parents. Clearly I was using something else as the basis for my moral decisions in which Church teachings I chose to agree with and which I chose to reject, but what was it?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;A Star Wars fan website (of all things [1]) led me to encounter the phrase "secular humanism". Reading up on that, I found it agreed perfectly with the criteria I had been applying in picking and choosing amongst the teachings of the Catholic Church. I was happy to have found a term for my beliefs that focused on what I believed in, rather than simply highlighting one thing I had chosen to reject (i.e. "atheism"). One cognitive science degree and a whole lot of reading later (including the likes of Dawkins, Dennett, Hofstadter, Pinker and Sagan), and I was even happier with the idea of a world where we create our own meaning rather than having it passed down to us from on high. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;The journey from childhood faith, through teenage agnosticism to adult faith and my eventual deliberate choice of a naturalistic world view was something that involved a lot of thought and introspection, that I was fortunate enough to have the time for. However, it left me with a problem. Many of my family are still devout (or not-so-devout) Catholics and my friends embrace a variety of religious traditions. How could I align what I had discovered for myself with their different points of view, without coming off (to myself or to others) as a condescending twit making allowances for the "less enlightened"? &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;The militant atheists (such as Dawkins) often come across as wanting to see the religious baby thrown out with the fundamentalist bathwater. Others (such as Dennett) are able to put forward a more nuanced view, that attempts to better understand the whole of religion, so that we can more effectively harness the positive aspects while reducing the negative effects. Having been a believer as an adult, and having suffered no significant negative experiences through my faith, I have a much easier time seeing the good side of religious belief than many atheists, so Dennett's line of rapprochement seemed far more appealing to me. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;Eventually, I was able to distil my personal ethos down into a belief that the pillars of ethical and moral living consist of just 5 basic concepts: honesty, compassion, justice, freedom and hope. As I see it, we have to believe in something, otherwise nihilism wins and there is no point in getting out of bed in the morning. For myself, and humanists like me, I see those five things as products of evolution. I see them as glorious, beautiful things in their own right, the most profound creations of the human race. It is up to each of us to honour and steward each of the principles as best we can. Others choose to see those 5 principles as something that was gifted to us by a higher power, rather than something we created collectively ourselves over the course of time. I don't agree with such beliefs, but that is only because I see them as unnecessary. In practice, if the outcome is a personal faith that accepts and promotes the same 5 principles I believe in, then I don't really care all that much as to why somebody agrees they're important. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;Where I start to have an issue is when groups and individuals either consciously or inadvertently start to disrespect those ideals. Whether the offenders are governments, organised religions, corporations, or specific individuals, malicious deceit, discounting of the feelings of others, inequitable treatment, unnecessary coercive restraints and excessive pessimism and fatalism are all concepts I have fundamental problems with. Of course, balancing all of those principles means that there are many situations encountered in the real world that have no right answers, only less bad wrong ones, which is why reasonable people may disagree on the correct courses of action. Simply "getting rid of religion" doesn't magically make the underlying issues go away. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;  The dangerous religions are the ones that create a priestly caste and then say to everyone else "It's complicated, it's a mystery, don't worry your pretty little head about it". By convincing people to shut down their capacity for critical thinking, they are trampling over a number of those principles I value (especially honesty and freedom). Religious traditions that instead encourage their believers to adopt an attitude of constant questioning are far more compatible with the humanist point of view, as it allows members of that faith to make their own judgments based on universal ethical principles in addition to the teachings of that specific tradition. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;This separation of beliefs from consequences (similar to the distinction made between beliefs and actions here at OCRT) and individual believers from religious organisations was the insight I needed to realise that it was possible to be religiously tolerant without feeling (or being) condescending about it. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;[1] For the record, it was &lt;a href="http://www.stardestroyer.net/"&gt;Stardestroyer.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/01/which-matters-more-to-you-being-right/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2011 17:21:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>An Ethos</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2010/12/ethos/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;(Note: I expanded this post into a &lt;a href="https://www.curiousefficiency.org/2011/01/which-matters-more-to-you-being-right.html"&gt;more comprehensive essay&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Somewhat inevitably, Howard Tayler's review of Voyage of the Dawn Treader over on the Schlock Mercenary blog got into something of a religious debate in the comments.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My &lt;a href="http://www.schlockmercenary.com/blog/dawn-treader#comment-110549921"&gt;contribution to the thread&lt;/a&gt; was an attempt at writing down the core concepts of a personal ethos I have been formulating over the last decade or so. I quite liked how it came out, so I figured I would capture it here as well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;For mine, I see the pillars of ethical and moral living as a belief in 5 basic concepts: honesty, compassion, justice, freedom and hope. We have to believe in &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;something&lt;/span&gt;, otherwise nihilism wins and there is no point in getting out of bed in the morning.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For myself, and humanists like me, I see those five things as products of evolution. I see them as glorious, beautiful things in their own right, the most profound creations of the human race. It is up to each of us to honour and steward each of the principles as best we can.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Others choose to see those 5 principles as something that was gifted to us by a higher power, rather than something we created collectively ourselves over the course of time. I don't &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;agree&lt;/span&gt; with such beliefs, but that is only because I see them as unnecessary. In practice, if the outcome is a personal faith that accepts and promotes the same 5 principles I believe in, then I don't really care all that much as to &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;why&lt;/span&gt; somebody agrees they're important.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Where I start to have an issue is when groups and individuals either consciously or inadvertently start to disrespect those ideals. Whether the offenders are governments, organised religions, corporations, or specific individuals, malicious deceit, discounting of the feelings of others, inequitable treatment, unnecessary coercive restraints and excessive pessimism and fatalism are all concepts I have fundamental problems with.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Of course, balancing all of those principles means that there are many situations encountered in the real world that have no right answers, only less bad wrong ones, which is why reasonable people may disagree on the correct courses of action. But "getting rid of religion" doesn't magically make the underlying issues go away.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;dangerous&lt;/span&gt; religions are the ones that create a priestly caste and then say to everyone else "It's complicated, it's a mystery, don't worry your pretty little head about it". By convincing people to shut down their capacity for critical thinking, they are trampling over a number of those principles I value (especially honesty and freedom). Religious traditions that instead encourage their believers to adopt an attitude of constant questioning are &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;far&lt;/span&gt; more compatible with the humanist point of view.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2010/12/ethos/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 07:19:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What he said</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2007/06/what-he-said/</link><dc:creator>Alyssa Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Occasionally you can come across an article which summarises your own thoughts so well, you don't really need to add anything. For me, the author's note on the linked webcomic is such an article.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2007/06/what-he-said/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2007 00:19:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>