<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency (philosophy draft)</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.curiousefficiency.org/categories/philosophy-draft.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 22:18:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>nikola</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>On Wielding Power</title><link>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making the usually implied disclaimer completely explicit on this one:
the views expressed in this article are my own, and do not necessarily
reflect the position of any organisations of which I am a member.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power is an interesting thing, and something that, as a society at large
(rather than the specialists that spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time thinking about it),
we really don't spend enough time giving serious consideration to. Trust and
fear, hope and despair, interwoven with the complex dynamics of
interpersonal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious kind of power is based on fear: people listening when you
tell them what to do, based on a fear of the consequences if they ignore
you. Many corporations have traditionally operated on this model: do what
you're told, or you'll be fired. "You might lose your job" then hangs as
an implicit threat behind every interaction with your management chain,
and a complex web of legal obligations and social safety nets has arisen
(to a greater or lesser degree in different countries) to help manage the
effectiveness of this threat and redress the power imbalance. This is also,
ultimately, the kind of power embodied in the legal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not the only kind of power though, and this post is largely about
another form of it: power based on &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Power based in trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear based power can be transferred fairly effectively: disobeying a
delegate can be punished as severely as disobeying the original authority
and so it goes. Interpersonal considerations don't get much consideration
in such environments - they're about getting the job done, without much
concern for the feelings of the people doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency of that kind of centralised control degrades fairly quickly
though - with everyone being in constant fear of punishment, a whole lot
of effort ends up being expended on figuring out what the orders are,
communicating the orders, ensuring the orders have been followed, requesting
new orders when the situation changes, recording exactly what was done to
implement the order and ensuring that if anything goes wrong it was the
original orders that were to blame rather than the people following them
and so on and so forth. It's like a human body that has no local reflexes,
but instead has to think through the idea of removing its hand from a
hotplate as an act of deliberate will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a different kind of power though, summed up well in this &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc"&gt;YouTube
video&lt;/a&gt;. What that kind of
power is based on is the idea that once people have their core survival
needs met, there are three key motivators that often work better than money:
autonomy, mastery and purpose. (Note: this is &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; core survival needs
are met. If people are still stressed about food, shelter, their health and
their personal relationships, then autonomy, mastery and purpose can go take
a hike)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its best, an environment based on autonomy, mastery and purpose is one
of mutual trust and respect. The purpose of the overall organisation and
its individual components is sufficiently well articulated that everyone
involved understands their obligations and how their efforts contribute to
the greater whole, individuals are given a high degree of autonomy in
determining how best to meet their obligations, and supported in the
pursuit of the required mastery to fulfil those obligations as well as
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of distributed trust that Silicon Valley &lt;em&gt;tries&lt;/em&gt; to sum up
in its "move fast and break things" motto, but fails miserably in doing so.
The reason? Those last two words there: "break things". It's an
incredibly technocratic view of the world, and one that leaves out the
most important element of any situation: the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a key point many technologists miss: ultimately, &lt;em&gt;technology doesn't
matter&lt;/em&gt;. It is not an end unto itself - it is only ever a means to an end,
and that end will almost always be something related to people (we humans
are an egocentric bunch). When you "break things" you &lt;em&gt;hurt people&lt;/em&gt;, directly
or indirectly. Now, maybe those things needed to be broken (and a lot of
them do). Maybe those things were already hurting people, and the change
just shifts (and hopefully lessens) the burden. But the specific phrasing
in the Silicon Valley motto is one of cavalier irresponsibility, of freedom
from consequences. "Don't think about the people that may be hurt by your
actions - just move fast and break things, that's what we do here!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is NOT OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it needs to be OK to break things, whether deliberately or by mistake.
Without that, "autonomy" becomes a myth, and we are left with stagnation.
However, there's a difference between doing so carelessly, without
accounting for the impact on those that may be harmed by the chosen course
of action, and doing so while taking full responsibility for the harm your
actions may have caused .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, it's time to shift topics a bit. I assure you they're actually
related, which should become clearer further down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a corporation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The glib answer here would be "a toxic cesspool of humanity", and I'll grant
that's a fair description of a lot of them (see the earlier observations
regarding fear based power). I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; a capitalist though (albeit one that is
strongly in favour of redistributive tax systems), so I see more potential
for good in them than many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm going to give my perspective on the way some of the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt; ones
work when running smoothly, at least in regards to three roles: the Chief
Financial Officer, the Chief Technology Officer and the Chief Executive
Officer. (You may choose not to believe me when I say non-toxic corporations
are a real thing, but I assure you, such companies &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; exist, as most
people &lt;em&gt;don't actually like&lt;/em&gt; working for toxic cesspools of humanity. It's
just that fully avoiding the descent into toxicity as organisations grow is,
as yet, an unsolved problem in society. Radical transparency does seem to
help a lot, though. Something about the cleansing power of sunlight and
competing centres of power...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CFO role is pretty straightforward: their job is to make sure that
everyone gets paid, and the company not only survives, but thrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CTO role is also pretty straightforward: they're the ultimate authority
on the technological foundations of an organisation. What's on the horizon
that they need to be aware of? What's growing old and needs to be phased out
in favour of something more recent? What just needs a bit of additional
investment to bring it up to scratch?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of a CEO is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; less clear. "Finance" is pretty clear, as is
"Technology". But what does "Executive" mean? They're not just in charge
of the executives - they're in charge of the whole company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take on it? The CEO is ultimately the "keeper of the company culture".
They ultimately decide not only &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; gets done, but also &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it gets
done. While they have a lot of other important responsibilities, a key one in
my mind is that it is the CEO's job to make sure that both the CFO and CTO
remember to account for the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; that will ultimately be tasked with
handling "execution". They're the ones that say "no, we're not cutting
that, it's important to the way we operate - we need to find another way
to save money" (remember, we're only talking about the &lt;em&gt;non-toxic&lt;/em&gt;
corporations here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when employees of a corporation expect that company to do the right
thing by them? They're trusting the CEO. Not the CFO. Not the CTO. The &lt;em&gt;CEO&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commenting on other people's business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that brings us to the specific reason I sat down to write this article: a
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450396296289869825"&gt;tweet I posted&lt;/a&gt;
earlier today regarding Mozilla's public debate over the board's choice of
CEO. Specifically, I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would take Eich accepting the Mozilla CEO role to mean his personal
pride matters more to him than Mozilla's mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a pretty bold statement to make about someone I don't know and have
never even met, and in relation to an organisation that I don't have any
direct relationship with beyond being a user of their software and a fan
of their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the things I didn't suggest. I didn't suggest he resign from his
existing position as CTO. I didn't suggest that the Mozilla board withdraw
their offer of the CEO position. However, I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; state that, from my
perspective as an outsider that wants to see Mozilla execute on their
mission to the best of their ability, "trust me" is a sufficiently big call
to have to make for a role as critical as the CEO position that I don't
believe Eich should be asking that of his fellow members of the Mozilla
community. Actions have consequences, and one of those consequences can be
"No, you no longer have the right to request our trust - you actively hurt
us, and we don't believe you when you say you wish to make amends".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Eich's credit, he at least didn't just say "trust me", but rather made a
number of
&lt;a href="https://brendaneich.com/2014/03/inclusiveness-at-mozilla/"&gt;specific commitments&lt;/a&gt;.
However, the time to build that credibility in a relatively open organisation
is &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; accepting such a significant role, not after. Otherwise, there
will always be a lingering doubt for affected individuals that any public
statements are a matter of the responsibilities of the position, rather than
a genuine change in personal convictions. When it comes to matters like a
commitment to inclusiveness you &lt;em&gt;don't want&lt;/em&gt; a CEO that is going through
the motions out of a sense of obligation: this stuff is hard work and
tempting to skimp on, even when you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; care about it at a personal level
(as a case in point - it would have been &lt;em&gt;so much easier&lt;/em&gt; for me to not
comment on this situation at all, that I almost left it at just a couple
of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450381744227643392"&gt;vague&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncoghlan_dev/status/450382065800728576"&gt;allusions&lt;/a&gt;
on Twitter rather than getting specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separating the personal from the professional is always difficult, and
few places moreso than the CEO role. During my tenure at Boeing, we had two
CEOs asked to resign due to unprofessional conduct. The military industrial
complex is a sordid mire of duplicitous misbehaviour and waste that makes
the open source technology community look like saints by comparison (and
I'll let you draw your own conclusions as to what it says about me
personally that I survived there for more than a decade), yet even they
were of the opinion that personal conduct &lt;em&gt;matters&lt;/em&gt; at the CEO level,
even moreso than in other less prominent roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, I personally do hope Eich's newfound commitment to
inclusiveness is genuine, and that the concerns raised regarding his
appointment as CEO prove to be unfounded. I'd prefer to live in a world
where the blog post linked above represents a genuine change of heart,
rather than being merely a tactical consideration to appease particular
groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, my opinion on this topic doesn't matter - it's now up to
Eich to demonstrate through his actions that he's worthy of the trust that
the Mozilla board have placed in him, and for concerned members of the
Mozilla community to decide whether they're willing to adopt a "wait and
see" approach as suggested, or if they consider that belated request in and
of itself to be an unacceptable breach of &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; trust.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>philosophy draft</category><guid>http://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/03/on-wielding-power.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 19:08:33 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>