<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Curious Efficiency (Posts about politics)</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.curiousefficiency.org/categories/politics.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 15:22:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>DTCA Public Consultation - Brisbane</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/dtca-public-consultation.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Asher Wolf
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Asher_Wolf/status/555909774596784129"&gt;alerted me&lt;/a&gt; (and
many others in the open source and cryptographic communities) to the
Australian Defence Trade Controls Act 2012, and the current public
consultation taking place around a bill proposing amendments to that act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being heavily involved in improving the security of open source
infrastructure like the &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/"&gt;Python Package Index&lt;/a&gt;
and the
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0466/"&gt;Python 2 reference interpreter&lt;/a&gt;,
working at a multinational open source vendor, and having an extensive
background in working under the constraints of the US International Traffic
in Arms regulations, Asher's concern caught my attention, since bad
legislation in this area can have significant chilling effects on legitimate
research and development activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I've escalated this legislation for review by the legal teams
at various open source companies and organisations, with a view to making
formal submissions to the
&lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/Consultation.asp"&gt;public consultation process&lt;/a&gt;
that is open until January 30th (ready for bills to be submitted for
consideration to federal parliament on February 23rd).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I was also able to attend the first public consultation session
held at the University of Queensland on January 19, so these are my
impressions based primarily on that sessions and my own experiences dealing
with ITAR. I'm not a lawyer and I haven't actually &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the legislation,
so I'm not going to pick up on any drafting errors, but I can at least speak
to the intent of the folks involved in moving this process forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to worry about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To folks encountering this kind of legislation for the first time, the
sheer scope of the
&lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/DSGL.asp"&gt;Defence and Strategic Goods List&lt;/a&gt;
can seem absolutely terrifying. This was very clear to me from some of the
questions various academics in the room were asking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this particular point, I can only say: &lt;em&gt;"Don't panic"&lt;/em&gt;. This isn't a
unique-to-Australia list, it's backed by a treaty called the
&lt;a href="http://www.wassenaar.org/"&gt;Wassenaar Arrangement&lt;/a&gt; - the DSGL represents
part of the implementation of that arrangement into Australian law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the laws implementing that arrangement are well drafted, everyone outside
the military industrial complex (and certain easily weaponised areas of
scientific research) can pretty much ignore them, while everyone
inside the military industrial complex (and the affected areas of research)
pays very close attention to them because we like not being in jail (and
because gunrunning is bad, and bioterrorism is worse, mmm'kay?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heavily regulated military supply chain is already scary enough, we &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
don't want to see the likely consequences of an unregulated one. (And if
you're tempted to make a snarky comment about the latter already being the
case, no, it really isn't. While folks can sometimes use overclassification
to avoid regulations they're supposed to be following, that still introduces
significant friction and inefficiencies into whatever they're doing. It's not
as good as people actually respecting the laws of the countries they're
supposedly defending, including genuinely meeting the requirement for
civilian authority over the military, but it's still a hell of a lot better
than nothing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting back on topic, the US ITAR and crypto export control laws are
currently considered the most strict implementation of the Wassenaar
Arrangement amongst the participating nations (going beyond the requirements
of the treaty in several areas), so if you see plenty of US nationals
participating in an activity without being fined and going to jail, you can
be fairly confident that it isn't actually a controlled activity under the
DSGL (or, even if it is, permits for that specific activity will be fairly
easy to get, and the most likely consequence of not realising you need a
permit for something you're doing will be someone from your government
getting in touch to point out that you should apply for one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certainly some very questionable aspects of this list (with the
perennial "favourite" being the fact the Wassenaar Arrangement does, in fact,
attempt to regulate the global trade in mathematics, which is just as stupid
and problematic as it sounds), but it's a known quantity, and one we're pretty
sure we can continue to live with (at least for the time being).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to worry about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real problem here is that the regulations included in the 2012 Act are
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; well drafted, and the legislated 2 year transition period from May 2013
through to May 2015 prior to the enforcement provisions kicking in is about
to run out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with the 2012 act is that in trying to keep things simple
(essentially, "if its on the DSGL, you need a permit"), it ended up becoming
extraordinarily draconian, requiring a permit for things that don't require
an export license even under ITAR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the general public, the most significant shift in the 2015 amendment bill
is the fact that several cases around open publication of information related
to dual-use technologies shift to being allowed by default, and only in
exceptional cases would a permit be required (and in those cases, the onus
would be on the government to inform the covered individuals of that
requirement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amendments also include a variety of additional exemptions for little
things like making it legal for Australian's own police and security agencies
to collaborate with their international counterparts. (Snarky comment
opportunity #2: in certain areas, making such collaboration illegal seems
like a potentially attractive idea...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That 2 year pilot was included in the original legislation as a safety
mechanism, the feedback from the associated steering group has been
extensive, and if things had gone according to plan, the relevant amendments
to the bill would have been passed last year in the spring sitting of federal
parliament, leaving DECO with at least 6 months to educate affected
organisations and individuals, and start issuing the now necessary permits
before the enforcement provisions became active in May. Unfortunately, we
currently have a federal government that views pushing a particular
ideological agenda as being more important than &lt;em&gt;actually doing their job&lt;/em&gt;,
so we're now faced with the prospect of regulations that industry doesn't
want, academia doesn't want, the Australian public service don't want, and
the Australian military don't want, coming into effect anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn't politics fun?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What DECO are (trying) to do about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group tasked with untangling this particular legislative Charlie Foxtrot
is the Australian Defence Export Control Office (DECO). Their proposal for
addressing the situation hinges on two bills that they plan to put before
the next sitting of federal parliament:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an amendment bill for the Act itself, which fixes it to be a conventional
  implementation of the Wassenaar Arrangement, in line with existing
  implementations in other Wassenaar nations (why we didn't just do that in
  the first place is beyond me, but at least DECO are trying to fix the
  mistake now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a second bill to delay the enactment of the enforcement provisions for
  a further six months to provide sufficient time for DECO to properly
  educate affected parties and start issuing permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I am aware, the second bill is needed primarily due to the
consideration of the first bill slipping by six months, since we're now
looking at the prospect of only having 4 weeks for DECO to start issuing
permits before the enforcement provisions come into effect. &lt;em&gt;Nobody&lt;/em&gt; involved
thinks that's a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If both of those bills pass promptly, then the only cause for concern is
whether or not there are any remaining devils in the details of the
legislation itself. Member of the general public aren't going to be able to
pick those up - despite the surface similarities, legalese isn't English, and
reading it without interpreting it in the context of relevant case law can be
a good way to get yourself into trouble. Summary translations from legalese
to English by a competent lawyer are a much safer bet, although still not
perfect. (For the programmers reading this: I personally find it useful
to think of legalese as source code that runs on the language interpreter of
a given nation's legal system, while the English translations are the code
comments and documentation that anyone should be able to read if they
understand the general concepts involved).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If at least the second bill passes, then we have another 6 months to work on
a better resolution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;neither&lt;/em&gt; bill passes, then DECO end up in a bad situation where they'll
be required by law to implement and enforce regulations that they're
convinced are a bad idea. They actually have everything in place to do that
if they have to, but they don't want this outcome, and neither does anyone
else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What industry and academia can do about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it's very short notice, the main thing industry and academia can do
is to file formal submissions with DECO as described in their overview of
the &lt;a href="http://www.defence.gov.au/deco/Consultation.asp"&gt;public consultation process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main things to be addressed on that front:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring federal parliament are aware of the importance of amending the
  Defence Trade Controls Act 2012 to eliminate the more draconian provisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring federal parliament are aware of the infeasibility of putting this
  into effect on the original timeline and the need for a significant delay
  in the introduction of the enforcement provisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensuring DECO are alerted to any remaining areas of concern in the
  specific drafting of the amended legislation (although I'd advise skipping
  this one if you're not a lawyer yourself - it's the functional equivalent
  of a lawyer with no training as a programmer proposing patches to the Linux
  kernel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were apparently asleep at the wheel when DTCA went through in 2012, so
we owe a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of thanks to whoever it was that advocated for and achieved
the inclusion of the two year transition and consultation period in the
original bill. Now we need to help ensure that our currently somewhat
dysfunctional federal parliament doesn't keep us from receiving the benefit
of that foresight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's definitely not going to happen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This consultation process is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the place to rail against the details of
the Wassenaar Arrangement or Australia's participation in it. You won't
achieve anything except to waste the time of folks that currently have a
really serious problem to fix, and a very limited window in which to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, Wassenaar has some serious problems, especially around its handling
of cryptography and cryptographic research, but we have a fairly settled
approach to handling that at this point in history. The critical concern in
this current case is to help DECO ensure that the associated Australian
regulations can be readily handled through the mechanisms that have already
been put in place to handle existing Wassenaar enforcement regimes in other
countries. With the way the 2012 Act was drafted, that's almost certainly
currently not the case, but the proposed 2015 amendments &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; fix it
(assuming the amendments actually have the effects that DECO has indicated
they're intended to).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>tech</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2015/01/dtca-public-consultation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 12:41:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Seven billion seconds per second</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, YouTube put together their
&lt;a href="http://www.onehourpersecond.com/"&gt;"One hour per second"&lt;/a&gt; site, visualising
the fact that for every second of time that elapses, an hour of video is
uploaded to YouTube. Their
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/yt/press/statistics.html"&gt;current statistics page&lt;/a&gt;
indicates that figure is now up to 100 hours per minute (about 1.7 hours per
second).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressive numbers to be sure. However, there's another set of numbers I
personally consider significantly more impressive: every second, more than
seven billion seconds are added to the tally of collective human existence
on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about that for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 7 billion seconds of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 117 million minutes of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 2 million hours of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 81 thousand days of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 11 thousand weeks of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick. Another 222 years of collective human existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience, every single second, of every
single day. And as the world population grows, it's only going to get faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;222 years of collective human experience per second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 centuries per minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;801 centuries per hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 millenia per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;135 millenia per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 billion years per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth in our collective human experience over the course of a single
year would stretch halfway back to the dawn of time if it was experienced
by an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We currently squander most of that potential. We allow a lot of it to be
wasted scrabbling for the basic means of survival like food, clean water and
shelter. We lock knowledge up behind closed doors, forcing people to reinvent
solutions to already solved problems because they can't afford the entry fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ascribe value to people based solely on their success in the resource
acquisition game that is the market economy, without acknowledging the large
degree to which sheer random chance is frequently the determinant in who wins
and who loses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We inflict bile and hate on people who have the temerity to say "I'm here,
I'm human, and I have a right to be heard", while being different from us.
We often focus on those superficial differences, rather than our underlying
common humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fight turf wars based on where we were born, the colour of our skin, and
which supernatural beings or economic doctrines we allow to guide our
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to change this? Is it possible to build a world where we
consider people to have inherent value &lt;em&gt;just because they're fellow
humans&lt;/em&gt;, rather than because of specific things they have done, or specific
roles they take up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly don't know, but it seems worthwhile to try. I certainly find it
hard to conceive of a better possible way to spend my own meagre slice of
those seven billion seconds per second :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>philosophy</category><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2014/09/seven-billion-seconds-per-second.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 07:35:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using the SOPA protests to highlight related problems in Australia</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/01/using-sopa-protests-to-highlight.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I  figure this is the easiest place to publish the message I just sent to  Larissa Waters, the Greens Senator that is one of Queensland's  representatives in the Federal Senate. I also wrote to Yvette D'ath (our  local MHR) a few days ago, but I didn't keep a copy of that one. Will  this achieve anything? Probably not, but hey, at least I tried (and if  none of their constituents ever write to them about it, our reps are  quite entitled to assume we're all OK with them selling out the county  to legacy US media interests): &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Senator Waters,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With  today being the day Wikipedia and a wide range of other sites have  either gone dark or taken other action to protest draconian internet  censorship legislation making its way through the US Congress, it seems  an opportune time to highlight our own government's ongoing concerning  behaviour on that front.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Of particular concern is their &lt;a href="http://delimiter.com.au/2012/01/17/govt-censors-secret-anti-piracy-meeting-notes/"&gt;continuing refusal&lt;/a&gt; to release details of a secretive meeting between government  representatives and representatives of the same organisations that are  behind the draconian US bills currently being protested. The government  even &lt;a href="http://delimiter.com.au/2011/12/23/secret-piracy-talks-govt-banned-consumer-groups/"&gt;deliberately excluded&lt;/a&gt; representatives of a number of community interest organisations that sought to attend these discussions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These  legacy media companies (aka horse drawn carriage manufacturers) are  flailing around wildly as the rise of free and open digital  communications networks (aka automobiles) threatens the cherished  gatekeeper role they have enjoyed for the past few decades as media  distributors. They have failed to adapt, and are increasingly being  bypassed as artists, writers, musicians, comedians and other media  creators find ways to use the power of the internet to connect more  directly with their fans. These direct connections are great for both  artists and fans, but place the intermediaries like YouTube, Apple  iTunes, Amazon, BandCamp, Flickr, etc, in the role of service providers  to the artists and fans rather than gatekeepers to widespread  distribution. Unfortunately, instead of going gracefully into that good  night, these organisations are investing inordinate sums of money  worldwide in lobbying for legislation that would make the permissive,  open practices of most of these new service providers a recipe for  prohibitively high legal liabilities, effectively making those practices  unsustainable and thus breaking the internet as we know it today.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Australia  already markedly shifted many intellectual monopoly policies to favour  the interests of US copyright holders at the expense of Australian  citizens when we signed the US-FTA some time ago. We have also  participated in the secretive process of drafting the  Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement, which spends far more time  considering digital copyright infringement than it does actual  counterfeiting. The current negotiations over membership in the  Trans-Pacific Partnership agreement raise legitimate fears that  Australia's intellectual monopoly policy will be shifted even further  towards the draconian position of the United State Trade Representative,  even as those policies are being protested strongly within the US  itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In line with your &lt;a href="http://greens.org.au/policies/human-rights-democracy/community-participation-in-government"&gt;published policy&lt;/a&gt; on community participation in government, do the Greens plan to  publicly question the government over their apparent willingness to  place the interest of large US companies ahead of those of individual  Australian citizens?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Regards,&lt;br&gt;Nick.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;</description><category>intarwebs</category><category>politics</category><category>tech</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2012/01/using-sopa-protests-to-highlight.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 09:47:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Climate change "skepticism": a text book case of the "Tragedy of the Commons"</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/climate-change-skepticism-text-book.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So, with the government moving to implement a carbon tax, the issue of climate change and attempts to mitigate it are once again a big deal here in Australia.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Inspired by a friend's comment comparing carbon taxes with fines for littering, along with a few of the  responses to that comment, I started pondering the similarities and differences between the current attempts to deal with carbon dioxide emissions, and the &lt;a href="http://www.edf.org/page.cfm?tagID=1085"&gt;effective cost internalisation schemes created&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990's that severely reduced industrial sulphur dioxide emissions, as well as various current laws that prohibit dumping of toxic waste in developed nations (and their &lt;a href="http://www.ehow.com/info_8012059_causes-dumping-third-world-countries.html"&gt;unintended side effects&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Fair warning before I wade in: I've simplified quite a few things, particularly on the acid rain front. This post is long enough as it is, without making it even longer with all the relevant caveats about other causes of acid rain and any other details I've glossed over as being irrelevant to the main point of the article. It's a general overview, not a peer reviewed scientific paper)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;A tale of two gases&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;The key similarity between sulphur dioxide induced acid rain and carbon dioxide induced global warming is hopefully fairly obvious: they both represent a classic economic "externality", a cost borne by someone other than the person responsible for causing it. The industries and individuals emitting these pollutants don't suffer any immediate harmful consequence through the normal action of nature.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In situations like that, regulation in one form or another is the only effective tool we have to ensure that at least some portion of those external costs is reflected back on the responsible individuals. As noted in the link above, this approach proved extraordinarily effective in reducing acid rain in the US, drastically cutting sulphur emissions at a fraction of the originally predicted cost.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, there are a few key differences that have contributed to the discussion over carbon dioxide taking a rather different path to that over sulphur dioxide:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's hard to deny the harmful effects of sulphur dioxide emissions when plants, fish and insects are dying due to the excessive levels of acidity in rain and ground water. By contrast, it is very hard to convey clearly why a small rise in average global temperatures is going to be such a bad thing, or even how human carbon dioxide emissions contribute to that happening.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Acid rain from sulphur emissions is generally a &lt;i&gt;local&lt;/i&gt; problem with local causes (from a continental perspective, anyway). Stop emitting sulphur dioxide in the US and acid rain stops falling in the US. Significantly reduce carbon dioxide emissions in Australia (or even the US) though, and we're likely still screwed if other countries don't follow suit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The "sulphur" cycle (how long it takes for the sulphur emissions to be deposited back on the ground as acid rain) is significantly shorter than that of carbon, so efforts to reduce emissions will have an effect on water acidity levels in a reasonably short time frame&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;Comparisons with anti-waste dumping laws are similar: the effects of toxic waste dumping are generally both local, obvious and able to be cleaned up within years rather than decades, so it is easy to get support for laws prohibiting such practices, even if the end result of those laws is just to export the problem to a poorer country.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Manufacturing doubt and exploiting the "Grey Fallacy"&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Acid rain is an easy problem to sell: the acid damages plants and objects directly, so the harm can be easily conveyed through pictures and videos. The problem of climate change, though is far, far harder to illustrate simply, since it is a signal buried in some very noisy weather patterns.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A fundamental issue is the fact that people don't really experience climate, but instead experience weather. The day to day and seasonal variations in the weather massively exceed the scale of the underlying trends being discussed by climate scientists. The fact that predicting the weather in a few days time is harder than predicting long term climate trends is actually massively counterintuitive, even though almost all scientists and engineers are familiar with the fact that random fluctuations at a small scale may average out to something almost perfectly predictable at a large scale (compare the unpredictable nature of quantum physics with the straightforward determinism of classical Newtonian mechanics).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We're also not really used to the idea of directly affecting the balance of the planet on a global scale. In absolute terms, the effects of the sun, the oceans and the plants on the carbon cycle all dwarf the human contribution. The idea that the non-human forcings were actually largely in balance with each other, and that the comparatively small human contribution is enough to tip that balance to the point of producing more carbon than can be absorbed by natural mechanisms is really quite a subtle one.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The scientific background needed to truly understand and come to grips with the hows and the whys of the IPCC predictions reminds me of &lt;a href="http://abstrusegoose.com/272"&gt;this comic&lt;/a&gt; regarding the knowledge needed to even begin to understand the vagaries of string theory (make sure to click through on the comic itself to see the whole chain of images).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If there wasn't anyone around with a vested interest in maintaining the status quo (at least for a while longer), this likely wouldn't be a problem. Scientists, politicians, economists and engineers could proceed with the development of mitigation strategies, while also attempting to educate the general populace as to the reasons behind any actions taken. Since such vested interests do exist, however, their opposition makes it significantly harder to convince the lay public that there is a real problem here.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Because climate science is such a complex topic, it is actually quite hard to explain to a non-scientist just &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; the scientific consensus is as strong as it is. If you oversimplify, you veer into territory where statements are so oversimplified that they border on being false. However, if you're coming from the other angle and want to persuade people that the science "isn't settled", then you're no longer constrained by the need to be accurate and can just go with whatever sounds more intuitively plausible and/or better caters to people's natural inclinations and prejudices.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sites like &lt;a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com/"&gt;Skeptical Science&lt;/a&gt; do their best to clearly explain why the oft-repeated "skeptic" arguments are basically BS (and do it well), but to someone only following the Cliff Notes mainstream media version of the debate, the temptation is still very, very strong to just assume the truth lies somewhere between the two positions being debated.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Telling people to "do their own research" doesn't really help all that much in practice. Telling the BS from the valid science is itself a fine art that takes a great deal of skill and experience. Being a veteran of arguments with creationists (and even intelligent design advocates) is actually quite beneficial, since the global warming "skeptics" use many of the same rhetorical tricks as creationists do when attempting to deny the fact of evolution (incessant use of such deceptive tactics is actually one of the major hints that someone is trying to sell you a line rather than just stating the truth as they see it). The most common tactic used by both groups is to drag out a thoroughly rebutted argument for each new audience, in hopes that they aren't aware of the existence of a rebuttal.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For example, just as most people can't answer "How could a bombardier beetle possibly evolve?" off the top of their heads - I've actually forgotten all of the plausible answers myself - neither can they answer questions like "If the climate is supposed to be warming, why is it colder now than it was during the Middle Ages?". While that one is actually fairly straightforward to answer (ice cores and other data shows that the medieval warming was likely localised to Europe due to various currents in the Atlantic, but this merely shifted heat around, so that other parts of the world were correspondingly colder), there are dozens of other oft-repeated thoroughly debunked arguments, and it's basically impossible for a mere interested observer to remember them all. As it turns out, I had actually misremembered the correct explanation for the Medieval warm period, so the point above isn't quite right and invites an attack on the grounds that I don't know what I'm what I'm talking about. To some extent that's actually true - my opinion on climate science issues is based on a meta-analysis of the trustworthiness of various information sources (including the full &lt;a href="http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_and_data_reports.shtml"&gt;IPCC reports&lt;/a&gt;), since I'm not inclined to spend a few decades studying up and redoing all the science myself. Fortunately, Skeptical Science has the &lt;a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com/medieval-warm-period.htm"&gt;full story&lt;/a&gt; for this question and many others (the MWP was actually colder than the latter half of this century, despite higher solar activity and lower volcanic activity), so correcting my error is the task of a few moments. And if you're still wondering about the bombardier beetle thing, TalkOrigins has the &lt;a href="http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/bombardier.html"&gt;full story for that&lt;/a&gt;, too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fortunately, at the decision making level here in Australia, this part of the debate seems to be coming to a close, with even Toby Abbott (the leader of the opposition) at least paying lip service to the fact that human-induced increases in average global temperatures are now a fact of life. However, the mainstream media is still happy to "teach the controversy" in the hopes of picking up a few more eyeballs (or ears) to sell to their advertisers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;But the problem is so much bigger than us!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, even once you get agreement that human-induced global warming due to excessive carbon dioxide emissions is a genuine problem, you then run into the "But we can't do anything about it!" attitude.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many Australians (including some elected members of our Federal parliament) go "Oh, but the US/Europe/Brazil/Russia/India/China have a much bigger impact than we do. Doing anything will hurt our international competitiveness without really achieving anything, so we shouldn't bother."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Even the higher emission countries point fingers at each other. The US won't budge until China does. The BRIC countries are waiting for the US to make a move, and use US inaction as justification for similarly doing nothing in the meantime.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An absolutely textbook "Tragedy of the Commons" reaction. And we know how that story ends, don't we? In the long run everybody loses, nobody wins.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How do you fix it? Rules, regulations and social pressure. The "community of nations" isn't just words. The complex web of interdependencies that spans the world gives countries real power to exert influence on each other. Once some countries start to make a move towards serious carbon emission control strategies, then that becomes a bargaining chip to use in international negotiations. Will it work? Who knows. The only thing we know for sure is that the more carbon we pump into the atmosphere over the next few decades, the higher the impact from global warming will be (it's now guaranteed that there will be &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; impact - the carbon cycle is too long for us to prevent that at this late stage of the game).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ideally you would want to adopt an emissions trading scheme along the lines of that used to curb sulfur emissions, but the wholehearted embrace of dodgy pseudoscience by far too many members of our Federal Opposition party spiked that particular barrel.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So a carbon tax it is (for now, anyway). The hysterical cries of "Oh my god, you've doomed the country!" ring loudly from those that will bear most of the direct costs of actually internalising the negative effects their carbon emissions have on the wider environment. Their motives are, to say the least, a little bit suspect. The political opportunism involved in our Federal Opposition leader backing them is disappointing, but unsurprising.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;In the PM's words&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's a nice summary of the current situation in a Fairfax &lt;a href="http://www.smh.com.au/opinion/politics/extreme-views-must-not-decide-carbon-tax-20110323-1c6ky.html"&gt;opinion piece&lt;/a&gt; that went out over Gillard's byline:&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;The longer we leave it the harder action on climate change gets. This reform road is a hard one to walk. Just as doing nothing is not an option, we need to be careful to ensure that we do not make decisions that will cost our economy and jobs.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;There's a definite risk that the government's plans won't live up to their ambitions. However, the world's past experience with the sulfur dioxide doomsayers should arouse some deep skepticism and not directed towards those wanting to press forward with plans to curb carbon emissions.</description><category>philosophy</category><category>politics</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/climate-change-skepticism-text-book.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Queensland's "unelected" leader of the opposition</title><link>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/queenslands-unelected-leader-of.html</link><dc:creator>Nick Coghlan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Following the declaration of Brisbane's Lord Mayor that he is running for state parliament at the next election, and will be the leader of the opposition for that campaign, there is a trope making the rounds that he is somehow "unelected".&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Out of curiosity, I decided to see how his numbers in the Brisbane City Council elections in 2008 stacked up against Anna Bligh's numbers in the 2009 state election.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The internet being what it is, official sources for these numbers weren't too hard to dig up:&lt;br&gt;I found the &lt;a href="http://www.brisbane.qld.gov.au/about-council/elections/previous-election-results/index.htm"&gt;Lord Mayoral&lt;/a&gt; results on the Brisbane City Council site&lt;br&gt;I found the &lt;a href="http://www.ecq.qld.gov.au/elections/state/state2009/results/district73.html"&gt;Electorate of South Brisbane&lt;/a&gt; results on the Electoral Commission Qld site (with the preferences taken into account &lt;a href="http://www.ecq.qld.gov.au/elections/state/state2009/results/summary.html#12"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Results:&lt;br&gt;Campbell Newman received 335,076 first preference votes for Lord Mayor (60% of the total).&lt;br&gt;After distribution of preferences, he received a total of 339,320 votes (66% of the total).&lt;br&gt;It's probably worth noting that the second placed candidate received 29% of the first round votes, increasing to 34% after distribution of preferences, so Newman actually did receive the majority of the remaining preferences, there just weren't many to go around.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Anna Bligh received 12,243 first preference votes in her electorate of South Brisbane (48% of the total).&lt;br&gt;After distribution of preferences, she received a total of 14,697 votes (65% of the total).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, our State Premier holds her position on the back of the support of her party and around 15k people living in or near South Brisbane.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The new leader of the opposition will hold that position on the back of the support of his party and around 340k people living in the City of Brisbane.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Since the current population of Qld is estimated at 4.5 million people, effectively 7.5% of the state voted for Newman to be Brisbane's Lord Mayor, while only 0.3% voted for Bligh to represent the seat of South Brisbane.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And people are calling &lt;i&gt;Newman&lt;/i&gt; an unelected leader?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Yes, I'm aware that the nature of parliamentary governments based on geographic representation means that most constituents don't get to vote directly for their parliamentary leaders. The only purpose of this post is to point out how &lt;i&gt;dumb&lt;/i&gt; that makes the "unelected" gibe sound when it is aimed at the directly elected Lord Mayor of a city the size of Brisbane)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.curiousefficiency.org/posts/2011/03/queenslands-unelected-leader-of.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 11:47:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>